<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml><records><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Hutter, Nils</author><author>Losch, Martin</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Scaling properties of Arctic sea ice deformation in a high-resolution viscous-plastic sea ice model and in satellite observations</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research</full-title></periodical><keywords><keyword>Arctic Ocean</keyword><keyword>High-resolution modeling</keyword><keyword>Scaling</keyword><keyword>Sea ice deformation</keyword><keyword>Sea ice rheology</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2018</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2017JC013119</electronic-resource-num><urls/><abstract>© 2018. American Geophysical Union. Sea ice models with the traditional viscous-plastic (VP) rheology and very small horizontal grid spacing can resolve leads and deformation rates localized along Linear Kinematic Features (LKF). In a 1 km pan-Arctic sea ice-ocean simulation, the small-scale sea ice deformations are evaluated with a scaling analysis in relation to satellite observations of the Envisat Geophysical Processor System (EGPS) in the Central Arctic. A new coupled scaling analysis for data on Eulerian grids is used to determine the spatial and temporal scaling and the coupling between temporal and spatial scales. The spatial scaling of the modeled sea ice deformation implies multifractality. It is also coupled to temporal scales and varies realistically by region and season. The agreement of the spatial scaling with satellite observations challenges previous results with VP models at coarser resolution, which did not reproduce the observed scaling. The temporal scaling analysis shows that the VP model, as configured in this 1 km simulation, does not fully resolve the intermittency of sea ice deformation that is observed in satellite data.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Stewart, Andrew L.</author><author>Klocker, Andreas</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Circum-Antarctic shoreward heat transport derived from an eddy- and tide-resolving simulation</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><volume>45</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2018</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2017GL075677</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Stewart, Klocker, Menemenlis - 2018 - Circum-Antarctic shoreward heat transport derived from an eddy- and tide-resolving simulation.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/2017GL075677</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Chassignet, Eric</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ocean State Estimation and Prediction in Support of Oceanographic Research</title><secondary-title>Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>51-56</pages><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2000</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.5670/oceanog.2000.34</electronic-resource-num><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>ATOC Consortium</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ocean climate change: Comparison of acoustic tomography, satellite altimetry and modeling</title><secondary-title>Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science</full-title></periodical><pages>1327-1332</pages><volume>281</volume><issue>5381</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1998</year></dates><urls/><abstract>Comparisons of gyre-scale acoustic and direct thermal measurements of heat content in the Pacific Ocean, satellite altimeter measurements of sea surface height, and results from a general circulation model show that only about half of the seasonal and year-to-year changes in sea level are attributable to thermal expansion. Interpreting climate change signals from fluctuations in sea level is therefore complicated. The annual cycle of heat flux is 150 ± 25 watts per square meter (peak-to-peak, corresponding to a 0.2°C vertically averaged temperature cycle); an interannual change of similar magnitude is also detected. Meteorological estimates of surface heat flux, if accurate, require a large seasonal cycle in the advective heat flux.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fukumori, Tl</author><author>Fukumori, Tl</author><author>Steele, M.</author><author>Steele, M.</author><author>Wang, O.</author><author>Wang, O.</author><author>Zhang, J.</author><author>Zhang, J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Towards eddy permitting estimates of the global-ocean and sea-ice circulations</title><secondary-title>Ecco2.Org</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Ecco2.Org</full-title></periodical><pages>1-10</pages><keywords/><dates><year>2005</year></dates><urls><web-urls><url>http://scholar.google.com/scholar?start=300&amp;hl=en&amp;cites=6746892656378338886#67</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Book Section">7</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Ponte, Rui M.</author><author>Evangelinos, C.</author><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Mazloff, Matthew R.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Vinogradov, S.</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Combining Altimetric and All Other Data with a General Circulation Model.</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of the 15 Years of Progress in Radar Altimetry Symposium</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the 15 Years of Progress in Radar Altimetry Symposium</full-title></periodical><volume>SP-614</volume><issue>614</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2006</year></dates><isbn>9290929251 | 9789290929253</isbn><urls/><abstract>The TOPEX/POSEIDON mission was formulated in conjunction with the World Ocean Circulation Experiment (WOCE). Although altimetric data are by far the largest ocean data set that emerged from that experiment, it was recognized from the outset that the best estimate of the ocean circulation and its variability would be made by combining all the data with a good general circulation model. The US ECCO-GODAE consortium has now produced useful estimates of the three-dimensional time evolving ocean circulation at 1 degree lateral resolution, 23 layers in the vertical, over the time period 1992-2004. At the present time, the solution represents a least-squares misfit to about 410 million separate observational constraints. A large variety of fields can be analyzed in the results, but the focus here will be on the overturning circulation and its changes over this time period. The residual model/data misfits raise difficult questions about remaining errors in the altimetric/geoid fields.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lee, T.</author><author>Fukumori, I.</author><author>Menemenlis, D.</author><author>Xing, Z.</author><author>Fu, L.-L.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Possible links between Indonesian throughflow and El Niño</title><secondary-title>Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society</full-title></periodical><volume>83</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2002</year></dates><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, D.</author><author>Stammer, D.</author><author>Wunsch, C.</author><author>Hill, C.</author><author>Marshall, J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Comparison of ATOC heat content estimates with combined estimates from a general circulation model and TOPEX/POSEIDON altimetry</title><secondary-title>Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</full-title></periodical><volume>100</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1996</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1121/1.417523</electronic-resource-num><urls/><abstract>To study the role of the oceans in climate, weather, and other ocean–atmosphere phenomena, one needs to observe a global‐scale turbulent fluid that is opaque to electromagnetic radiation. Acoustic tomography and satellite altimetry provide complementary observational technologies for this purpose: Tomography provides path‐averaged heat content estimates with a degree of vertical resolution commensurate with the number of resolved acoustic rays or modes; altimetry provides depth‐integrated heat content estimates with good horizontal coverage but with additional contributions from the wind‐driven circulation and from uncertainties in the mass and salt budgets. These data, in combination with the dynamical descriptions embodied in general circulation models, are powerful tools for monitoring large‐scale oceanic variability. As a first step toward the demonstration of a complete system, heat content estimates obtained by the acoustic thermometry of ocean climate (ATOC) project are compared with those obtained by constraining the MIT ocean circulation model with TOPEX/POSEIDON altimeter data. This work extends a technique that has already been successfully deployed to make basin scale state estimates in the Western Mediterranean. © 1996, Acoustical Society of America. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Chechelnitsky, Michael</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Error Estimates for an Ocean General Circulation Model from Altimeter and Acoustic Tomography Data</title><secondary-title>Monthly Weather Review</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Monthly Weather Review</full-title></periodical><pages>763-778</pages><volume>128</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2000</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/1520-0493(2000)128&lt;0763:EEFAOG&gt;2.0.CO;2</electronic-resource-num><urls><web-urls><url>http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/abs/10.1175/1520-0493%282000%29128%3C0763%3AEEFAOG%3E2.0.CO%3B2</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>An offline approach is proposed for the estimation of model and data error covariance matrices whereby covariance matrices of model data residuals are &quot;matched&quot; to their theoretical expectations using familiar least-squares methods. This covariance matching approach is both a powerful diagnostic tool for addressing theoretical questions and an efficient estimator for real data assimilation studies. Provided that model and data errors are independent, that error propagation is approximately linear, and that an observability condition is met, it is in theory possible to fully resolve covariance matrices for both model and data errors. In practice, however, due to large uncertainties in sample estimates of covariance matrices, the number of statistically significant parameters that can be estimated is two to three orders of magnitude smaller than the total number of independent observations. The covariance matching approach is applied in the North Pacific (5°-60° N, 132°-252° E) to TOPEX/Poseidon sea level anomaly data, acoustic tomography data from the Acoustic Thermometry of Ocean Climate Project, and a GCM. A reduced state linear model that describes large-scale internal (baroclinic) error dynamics is constructed. Twin experiments suggest that altimetric data are ill suited to estimating the statistics of the vertical GCM error structure, but that such estimates can in theory be obtained using acoustic data. The particular GCM integration exhibits a warming trend relative to TOPEX/Poseidon data of order 1 cm yr-1 corresponding to a peak warming of up to 0.2°C yr-1 in the acoustic data at depths ranging from 50 to 200 m. At the annual cycle, GCM and TOPEX/Poseidon sea level anomaly are in phase, but GCM amplitude is 2 cm smaller, with the error confined above 200-m depth. After removal of trends and annual cycles, the low-frequency/wavenumber (periods &gt;2 months, wavelengths &gt;16°) TOPEX/Poseidon sea level anomaly is order 6 cm2. The GCM explains about 40% of that variance. By covariance matching, it is estimated that 60% of the GCM-TOPEX/Poseidon residual variance is consistent with the reduced state linear model.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Newspaper Article">5</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ngeve, Magdalene N.</author><author>van der Stocken, Tom</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Koedam, Nico</author><author>Triest, Ludwig</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Hidden founders? Strong bottlenecks and fine-scale genetic structure in mangrove populations of the Cameroon Estuary complex</title><secondary-title>Hydrobiologia</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Hydrobiologia</full-title></periodical><pages>1-19</pages><keywords><keyword>African mangroves</keyword><keyword>Connectivity</keyword><keyword>Dispersal</keyword><keyword>Effective population size</keyword><keyword>Gene flow</keyword><keyword>Hydrochory</keyword><keyword>Mangrove expansion</keyword><keyword>Ocean currents</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s10750-017-3369-y</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Ngeve Tom Van der Stocken Dimitris Menemenlis Nico Koedam Ludwig Triest - Unknown - Hidden founders Strong bottlenecks and fine-scale ge.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Fine-scale genetic structure (FSGS) is common in plants, driven by several ecological and evolutionary processes, among which is gene flow. Mangrove trees rely on ocean surface currents to spread their hydrochorous propagules through space. Since pollen dispersal is generally restricted to local scales, high level of short-distance propagule dispersal is expected to result in FSGS in Rhizophora spp. We investigated FSGS, recent bottleneck events, as well as historical and contemporary expansion patterns in Rhizophora racemosa populations from the entire coast of Cameroon, using 11 polymorphic microsatel-lite markers. Populations of the Cameroon Estuary complex (CEC) showed significant FSGS and significant reduction in effective population sizes (recent bottlenecks), compared to the other areas. Additionally, our results indicate stark differences between historical and contemporary expansion mod-els. These suggest that contemporary processes such as restricted propagule dispersal, bottleneck events from high indirect and direct anthropogenic pressure, and recolonization by founders from ancient local pockets/refugia most plausibly shape the patterns of FSGS in the CEC.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Bowman, Kevin W.</author><author>Liu, Junjie</author><author>Bloom, A. Anthony</author><author>Parazoo, Nicholas C.</author><author>Lee, Meemong</author><author>Jiang, Z.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Gierach, Michelle M.</author><author>Collatz, George James</author><author>Gurney, Kevin R.</author><author>Wunch, Debra</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Global and Brazilian carbon response to El Niño Modoki 2011-2010</title><secondary-title>Earth and Space Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth and Space Science</full-title></periodical><pages>637-660</pages><volume>4</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2016EA000204</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Bowman et al. - 2017 - Global and Brazilian carbon response to El Niño Modoki 2011-2010.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/2016EA000204</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The El Ni\~{n}o Modoki in 2010 lead to historic droughts in Brazil. We quantify the global and Brazilian carbon response to this event using the NASA Carbon Monitoring System Flux (CMS-Flux) framework. Satellite observations of CO$_2$, CO, and solar induced fluorescence (SIF) are ingested into a 4D-variational assimilation system driven by carbon cycle models to infer spatially resolved carbon fluxes including net ecosystem exchange, biomass burning, and gross primary productivity (GPP). The global net carbon flux tendency, which is the flux difference 2011-2010 and is positive for net fluxes into the atmosphere, was estimated to be -1.60 PgC between 2011-2010 while the Brazilian tendency was -0.24 $\pm$ 0.11 PgC. This estimate is broadly within the uncertainty of previous aircraft based estimates restricted to the Amazonian basin. The biomass burning tendency in Brazil was -0.24 $\pm$ 0.036 PgC, which implies a near-zero change of the net ecosystem production (NEP). The near-zero change of the NEP is the result of quantitatively comparable increase in GPP (0.34 $\pm$ 0.20) and respiration in Brazil. Comparisons of the component fluxes in Brazil to the global fluxes show a complex balance between regional contributions to individual carbon fluxes such as biomass burning, and their net contribution to the global carbon balance, i.e., the Brazilian biomass burning tendency is a significant contributor to the global biomass burning tendency but the Brazilian net flux tendency is not a dominant contributor to the global tendency. These results show the potential of multiple satellite observations to help quantify the spatially resolved response of productivity and respiration fluxes to climate variability.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Liu, Junjie</author><author>Bowman, Kevin W.</author><author>Schimel, David S.</author><author>Parazoo, Nicolas C.</author><author>Jiang, Zhe</author><author>Lee, Meemong</author><author>Bloom, A. Anthony</author><author>Wunch, Debra</author><author>Frankenberg, Christian</author><author>Sun, Ying</author><author>O’Dell, Christopher W.</author><author>Gurney, Kevin R.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Gierach, Michelle</author><author>Crisp, David</author><author>Eldering, Annmarie</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Contrasting carbon cycle responses of the tropical continents to the 2015–2016 El Niño</title><secondary-title>Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science</full-title></periodical><pages>eaam5690</pages><volume>358</volume><issue>6360</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><accession-num>29026011</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1126/science.aam5690</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Liu et al. - 2017 - Contrasting carbon cycle responses of the tropical continents to the 2015–2016 El Niño.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.sciencemag.org/lookup/doi/10.1126/science.aam5690</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The 2015-2016 El Niño led to historically high temperatures and low precipitation over the tropics, while the growth rate of atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2) was the largest on record. Here we quantify the response of tropical net biosphere exchange, gross primary production, biomass burning, and respiration to these climate anomalies by assimilating column CO2, solar-induced chlorophyll fluorescence, and carbon monoxide observations from multiple satellites. Relative to the 2011 La Niña, the pantropical biosphere released 2.5 ± 0.34 gigatons more carbon into the atmosphere in 2015, consisting of approximately even contributions from three tropical continents but dominated by diverse carbon exchange processes. The heterogeneity of the carbon-exchange processes indicated here challenges previous studies that suggested that a single dominant process determines carbon cycle interannual variability.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Savage, Anna C</author><author>Arbic, Brian K</author><author>Alford, Matthew H</author><author>Ansong, Joseph K</author><author>Farrar, J.Thomas</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>O'Rourke, Amanda K.</author><author>Richman, James G</author><author>Shriver, Jay F</author><author>Voet, Gunnar</author><author>Wallcraft, Alan J</author><author>Zamudio, Luis</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Spectral decomposition of internal gravity wave sea surface height in global models</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2017JC013009</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Savage et al. - Unknown - Spectral decomposition of internal gravity wave sea surface height in global models.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/2017JC013009</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Two global ocean models ranging in horizontal resolution from 1/128 to 1/488 are used to study the space and time scales of sea surface height (SSH) signals associated with internal gravity waves (IGWs). Frequency-horizontal wavenumber SSH spectral densities are computed over seven regions of the world ocean from two simulations of the HYbrid Coordinate Ocean Model (HYCOM) and three simulations of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm). High wavenumber, high-frequency SSH variance follows the predicted IGW linear dispersion curves. The realism of high-frequency motions (&gt;0:87 cpd) in the models is tested through comparison of the frequency spectral density of dynamic height variance computed from the highest-resolution runs of each model (1/258 HYCOM and 1/488 MITgcm) with dynamic height variance frequency spectral density computed from nine in situ profiling instruments. These high-frequency motions are of particular interest because of their contributions to the small-scale SSH variability that will be observed on a global scale in the upcoming Surface Water and Ocean Topography (SWOT) satellite altimetry mission. The variance at supertidal frequencies can be comparable to the tidal and low-frequency variance for high wavenumbers (length scales smaller than 50 km), especially in the higher-resolution simulations. In the highest-resolution simulations, the high-frequency variance can be greater than the low-frequency variance at these scales.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fenty, Ian G.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Zhang, Hong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Global coupled sea ice-ocean state estimation</title><secondary-title>Climate Dynamics</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Climate Dynamics</full-title></periodical><pages>931-956</pages><volume>49</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>4DVAR</keyword><keyword>Adjoint</keyword><keyword>Assimilation</keyword><keyword>Coupled ocean model</keyword><keyword>ECCO2</keyword><keyword>Sea ice</keyword><keyword>Sea ice concentration data</keyword><keyword>State estimation</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s00382-015-2796-6</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fenty, Menemenlis, Zhang - 2017 - Global coupled sea ice-ocean state estimation.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>© 2015 Springer-Verlag Berlin HeidelbergWe study the impact of synthesizing ocean and sea ice concentration data with a global, eddying coupled sea ice-ocean configuration of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model with the goal of reproducing the 2004 three-dimensional time-evolving ice-ocean state. This work builds on the state estimation framework developed in the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean consortium by seeking a reconstruction of the global sea ice-ocean system that is simultaneously consistent with (1) a suite of in situ and remotely-sensed ocean and ice data and (2) the physics encoded in the numerical model. This dual consistency is successfully achieved here by adjusting only the model’s initial hydrographic state and its atmospheric boundary conditions such that misfits between the model and data are minimized in a least-squares sense. We show that synthesizing both ocean and sea ice concentration data is required for the model to adequately reproduce the observed details of the sea ice annual cycle in both hemispheres. Surprisingly, only modest adjustments to our first-guess atmospheric state and ocean initial conditions are necessary to achieve model-data consistency, suggesting that atmospheric reanalysis products remain a leading source of errors for sea ice-ocean model hindcasts and reanalyses. The synthesis of sea ice data is found to ameliorate misfits in the high latitude ocean, especially with respect to upper ocean stratification, temperature, and salinity. Constraining the model to sea ice concentration modestly reduces ICESat-derived Arctic ice thickness errors by improving the temporal and spatial evolution of seasonal ice. Further increases in the accuracy of global sea ice thickness in the model likely require the direct synthesis of sea ice thickness data.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Cai, Cilan</author><author>Rignot, Eric</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Nakayama, Yoshihiro</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Observations and modeling of ocean-induced melt beneath Petermann Glacier Ice Shelf in Northwestern Greenland</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>8396-8403</pages><volume>44</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2017GL073711</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Cai et al. - 2017 - Observations and modeling of ocean-induced melt beneath Petermann Glacier Ice Shelf in Northwestern Greenland.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/2017GL073711</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Nakayama, Y.</author><author>Menemenlis, D.</author><author>Schodlok, M.</author><author>Rignot, E.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Amundsen and Bellingshausen Seas simulation with optimized ocean, sea ice, and thermodynamic ice shelf model parameters</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>1-16</pages><keywords><keyword>Amundsen Sea</keyword><keyword>Bellingshausen Sea</keyword><keyword>Glacial melt water</keyword><keyword>Pine Island Glacier</keyword><keyword>Thermocline</keyword><keyword>Winter water</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2016JC012538</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Nakayama et al. - 2017 - Amundsen and Bellingshausen Seas simulation with optimized ocean, sea ice, and thermodynamic ice shelf model pa.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Vazquez-Cuervo, Jorge</author><author>Torres, Hector S.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Chin, Toshio M.</author><author>Armstrong, Edward M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Relationship between SST gradients and upwelling off Peru and Chile: model/satellite data analysis</title><secondary-title>International Journal of Remote Sensing</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>International Journal of Remote Sensing</full-title></periodical><pages>6599-6622</pages><volume>38</volume><issue>23</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/01431161.2017.1362130</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Vazquez-Cuervo et al. - 2017 - Relationship between SST gradients and upwelling off Peru and Chile modelsatellite data analysis.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1080/01431161.2017.1362130</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The upwelling system off Peru/Chile is characterized by significant mesoscale to submesoscale surface variability that results from the instability of the coastal currents (due to the strong vertical and horizontal shears) and to the marked density cross-shore gradients (associated with the mean upwelling). Here we investigate to what extent upwelling intensity can be inferred from sea surface tem- perature (SST) derived from remote sensing. As a first step in validation, a comparison between SST observations is performed, which indicates that the 1 km gridded multi-scale ultra-high-resolu- tion (MUR) SST data set is defining a zone of maximum SST gradi- ents closer to shore than the low-resolution National Centers for Environmental Information 0.25° resolution data set. Two model versions, at nominal resolutions of 2 km and 4 km, of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model are analysed. A high-resolution version at 2 km is examined for the period 13 September 2011–23 January 2013, while a 4 km version is examined for 6 March 2011–22 April 2013. MUR shows maxima SST gradients in the range of 0.03 ± 0.02 K km−1 while the model showed higher gradients around 0.05 ± 0.02 K km−1. Based on coherence spectra, the relationship between upwelling rate (as inferred from the vertical velocity) and SST gradient is documented in the model from intraseasonal to annual timescales. It suggests that changes in SST gradient magnitudes are related to changes in the intensity of coastal upwelling off Peru and Chile. Such a relation- ship between SST gradients and vertical velocity would allow for the use of satellite-derived SSTs to monitor the intensity of coastal upwelling from the intraseasonal to annual timescales.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ardhuin, F.</author><author>Gille, Sarah T.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Rocha, Cesar B.</author><author>Rascle, N.</author><author>Chapron, B.</author><author>Gula, Jonathan</author><author>Molemaker, M. Jeroen</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Small-scale open ocean currents have large effects on wind wave heights</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research:Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research:Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>4500- 4517</pages><volume>122</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2016JC012413</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Ardhuin et al. - 2017 - Small-scale open ocean currents have large effects on wind wave heights.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Spreen, Gunnar</author><author>Kwok, Ronald</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Nguyen, An T.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sea-ice deformation in a coupled ocean-sea-ice model and in satellite remote sensing data</title><secondary-title>The Cryosphere</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>The Cryosphere</full-title></periodical><pages>1-37</pages><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.5194/tc-2016-13</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Spreen et al. - 2017 - Sea-ice deformation in a coupled ocean-sea-ice model and in satellite remote sensing data.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.the-cryosphere-discuss.net/tc-2016-13/</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>A realistic representation of sea-ice deformation in models is important for accurate simulation of the sea-ice mass balance. Simulated sea-ice deformation from numerical simulations with 4.5, 9, and 18 km horizontal grid spacing and a viscous–plastic (VP) sea-ice rheology are compared with synthetic aperture radar (SAR) satellite observations (RGPS, RADARSAT Geophysical Processor System) for the time period 1996–2008. All three simulations can reproduce the large-scale ice deformation patterns, but small-scale sea- ice deformations and linear kinematic features (LKFs) are not adequately reproduced. The mean sea-ice total deforma- tion rate is about 40 % lower in all model solutions than in the satellite observations, especially in the seasonal sea-ice zone. A decrease in model grid spacing, however, produces a higher density and more localized ice deformation fea- tures. The 4.5 km simulation produces some linear kinematic features, but not with the right frequency. The dependence on length scale and probability density functions (PDFs) of absolute divergence and shear for all three model solutions show a power-law scaling behavior similar to RGPS obser- vations, contrary to what was found in some previous studies. Overall, the 4.5km simulation produces the most realistic divergence, vorticity, and shear when compared with RGPS data. This study provides an evaluation of high and coarse- resolution viscous–plastic sea-ice simulations based on spa- tial distribution, time series, and power-law scaling metrics.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Seroussi, H</author><author>Nakayama, Yoshihiro</author><author>Larour, Eric Y.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Morlighem, M.</author><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author><author>Khazendar, Ala</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Continued retreat of Thwaites Glacier, West Antarctica, controlled by bed topography and ocean circulation</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>1-9</pages><volume>44</volume><keywords><keyword>10.1002/2017GL072910 and ice sheet dynamics</keyword><keyword>ocean</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2017GL072910</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Seroussi et al. - 2017 - Continued retreat of Thwaites Glacier, West Antarctica, controlled by bed topography and ocean circulation.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/2017GL072910</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Van der Stocken, Tom</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Modelling mangrove propagule dispersal trajectories using high-resolution estimates of ocean surface winds and currents</title><secondary-title>Biotropica</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Biotropica</full-title></periodical><pages>1-10</pages><volume>0</volume><issue>0</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/btp.12440</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Van der Stocken, Menemenlis - 2017 - Modelling mangrove propagule dispersal trajectories using high-resolution estimates of ocean surfac.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1111/btp.12440</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Nguyen, An T.</author><author>Kwok, Ronald</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Source and Pathway of the Western Arctic Upper Halocline in a Data-Constrained Coupled Ocean and Sea Ice Model</title><secondary-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>802-823</pages><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2012</year></dates><isbn>0022-3670</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/JPO-D-11-040.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Nguyen, Kwok, Menemenlis - 2012 - Source and Pathway of the Western Arctic Upper Halocline in a Data-Constrained Coupled Ocean and Sea I.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A coupled ocean and sea ice model is used to investigate dense water (DW) formation in the Chukchi and Bering shelves and the pathways by which this water feeds the upper halocline. Two 1992-2008 data-constrained solutions at 9- and 4-km horizontal grid spacing show that 1) winter sea ice growth results in brine rejection and DW formation; 2) the DW flows primarily down Barrow and Central-Herald Canyons in the form of bottom-trapped, intermittent currents to depths of 50-150 m from the late winter to late summer seasons; and 3) eddies with diameters similar to 30 km carry the cold DW from the shelf break into the Canada Basin interior at depths of 50-150 m. The 4-km data-constrained solution does not show eddy transport across the Chukchi Shelf at shallow depths; instead, advection of DW downstream of polynya regions is driven by a strong (similar to 0.1 m s(-1)) mean current on the Chukchi Shelf. Upper halocline water (UHW) formation rate was obtained from two methods: one is based on satellite data and on a simple parameterized approach, and the other is computed from the authors' model solution. The two methods yield 5740 +/- 61420 km(3) yr(-1) and 4190-4860 +/- 61440 km(3) yr(-1), respectively. These rates imply a halocline replenishment period of 10-21 yr. Passive tracers also show that water with highest density forms in the Gulf of Anadyr and along the eastern Siberian coast immediately north of the Bering Strait. These results provide a coherent picture of the seasonal development of UHW at high spatial and temporal resolutions and serve as a guide for improving understanding of water-mass formation in the western Arctic Ocean.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Antipodal acoustic thermometry: 1960, 2004</title><secondary-title>Deep-Sea Research Part I: Oceanographic Research Papers</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Deep-Sea Research Part I: Oceanographic Research Papers</full-title></periodical><pages>1-20</pages><volume>86</volume><keywords><keyword>Acoustic tomography</keyword><keyword>Antipodal acoustics</keyword><keyword>Climate change</keyword><keyword>Ocean modeling</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2014</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.dsr.2013.12.008</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dushaw, Menemenlis - 2014 - Antipodal acoustic thermometry 1960, 2004.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>On 21 March 1960, sounds from three 300-lb depth charges deployed at 5.5-min intervals off Perth, Australia were recorded by the SOFAR station at Bermuda. The recorded travel time of these signals, about 13,375s, is a historical measure of the ocean temperature averaged across several ocean basins. The 1960 travel time measurement has about 3-s precision. High-resolution global ocean state estimates for 2004 from the &quot;Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean, Phase II&quot; (ECCO2) project were combined with ray tracing to determine the paths followed by the acoustic signals. The acoustic paths are refracted geodesics that are slightly deflected by either small-scale topographic features in the Southern Ocean or the coast of Brazil. The refractive influences of intense, small-scale oceanographic features, such as Agulhas Rings or eddies in the Antarctic Circumpolar Current, greatly reduce the necessary topographic deflection and cause the acoustic paths to meander in time. The ECCO2 ocean state estimates, which are constrained by model dynamics and available data, were used to compute present-day travel times. Measured and computed arrival coda were in good agreement. Based on recent estimates of warming of the upper ocean, the travel-time change over the past half-century was nominally expected to be about -9s, but little difference between measured (1960) and computed (2004) travel times was found. Taking into account uncertainties in the 1960 measurements, the 2004 ocean state estimates, and other approximations, the ocean temperature averaged along the sound channel axis over the antipodal paths has warmed at a rate less than about 4.6m??Cyr-1 (95% confidence). At this time, the estimated uncertainties are comparable in size to the expected warming signal, however. ?? 2014 The Authors.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Report">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Recent North Pacific Climatology for ATOC</title></titles><periodical/><issue>30</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1994</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Wunsch - 1994 - Recent North Pacific Climatology for ATOC.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Line-averaged measurement of velocity fine structure in the ocean using acoustical reciprocal transmission</title><secondary-title>International Journal of Remote Sensing</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>International Journal of Remote Sensing</full-title></periodical><pages>267-281</pages><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1994</year></dates><isbn>0143116940</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/01431169408954070</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis - 1994 - Line-averaged measurement of velocity fine structure in the ocean using acoustical reciprocal transmission.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Reciprocal acoustical travel time measurements over paths of several hundred metres can be used to probe the statistical behaviour of turbulent velocity fine structure in the ocean. For homogeneous isotropic flows, and for long measuring baselines, an analytic expression relating line-averaged and point measurements of velocity is derived. Anisotropic and inhomogeneous flows are also considered. Correction formulas for the spatial and temporal variability of advection velocity along the measuring baseline are obtained. Practical limitations are established and experimental data from the arctic boundary layer beneath ice is compared with the theory. © 1994 Taylor &amp; Francis Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Davis, Russ E.</author><author>Fu, Lee-Lueng</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Giering, Ralf</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Marotzke, Jochem</author><author>Marshall, John C.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Niiler, Pearn Peter</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Zlotnicki, Victor</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ocean state estimation in support of CLIVAR and GODAE</title><secondary-title>International WOCE Newsletter</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>International WOCE Newsletter</full-title></periodical><keywords/><dates><year>2000</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Stammer et al. - 2000 - Ocean state estimation in support of CLIVAR and GODAE.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Czipott, Peter V.</author><author>Levine, Murray D.</author><author>Paulson, Clayton A.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Farmer, David M.</author><author>Williams, Robin G.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ice flexure forced by internal wave packets in the Arctic Ocean.</title><secondary-title>Science (New York, N.Y.)</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science (New York, N.Y.)</full-title></periodical><pages>832-835</pages><volume>254</volume><issue>5033</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1991</year></dates><accession-num>17787172</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1126/science.254.5033.832</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Czipott et al. - 1991 - Ice flexure forced by internal wave packets in the Arctic Ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17787172</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Tiltmeters on the Arctic Ocean were used to measure flexure of the ice forced by an energetic packet of internal waves riding the crest of diurnal internal bores emanating from the Yermak Plateau, north of the Svalbard Archipelago. The waves forced an oscillatory excursion of 36 microradians in tilt of the ice, corresponding to an excursion of 16 micrometers per second in vertical velocity at the surface and of 3.5 millimeters in surface displacement. Strainmeters embedded in the ice measured an excursion of 3 x 10(-7) in strain, consistent with ice flexure rather than compression. The measured tilt is consistent with direct measurements of excursions in horizontal current near the surface (12 centimeters per second) and in vertical displacement (36 meters) of the pycnocline 100 meters below the surface.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">3</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Howe, Bruce M.</author><author>Cornuelle, Bruce D.</author><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mercer, James A.</author><author>Munk, Walter H.</author><author>Spindel, Robert C.</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Zarnetske, M. R.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Acoustic remote sensing of large-scale temperature variability in the North Pacific Ocean</title><secondary-title>OCEANS `04 MTS/IEEE TECHNO-OCEAN</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>OCEANS `04 MTS/IEEE TECHNO-OCEAN</full-title></periodical><pages>1504-1506</pages><volume>1-4</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><isbn>0-7803-8669-8</isbn><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Howe et al. - 2004 - Acoustic remote sensing of large-scale temperature variability in the North Pacific Ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Large-scale, depth-averaged temperatures have been measured by long-range acoustic transmissions in the North Pacific Ocean for the past nine years. Acoustic sources located off central California and north of Kauai transmitted to receivers distributed throughout the North Pacific from 1996 through 1999 during the Acoustic Thermometry of Ocean Climate (ATOC) project. The Kauai transmissions resumed in early 2002 and are now continuing as part of the North Pacific Acoustic Laboratory (NPAL) project; a six-year time series has been obtained so far. Even at long time and large spatial scales the ocean is highly variable. The paths from Kauai to California show a modest cooling trend (longer travel times) until the present time. A path to the northwest showed modest warming and a weak annual cycle from 1999 until early 2003, when a strong annual cycle returned. In retrospect, these changes stemmed from the warming of the central Pacific that occurred in this interval, possibly associated with the Pacific Decadal Oscillation (PDO). Comparisons between measured travel times and those predicted using ocean models, constrained by satellite altimeter and other data, show significant similarities and differences. Comparison between upper-ocean Argo profiling float temperatures and the acoustically measured temperature along one path illustrates the strength of the integral measurements, with substantially lower uncertainty. The acoustic data ultimately need to be combined with sea-surface height Argo float data to determine the complementarity of the various data types. In particular, combining the acoustic and Argo data by inverse techniques will quantify the ability of the float data to resolve large-scale, upper-ocean heat content and the ability of the acoustic data to resolve abyssal temperature changes. © 2004 IEEE.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Cornuelle, Bruce D.</author><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Howe, Bruce M.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mercer, James A.</author><author>Munk, Walter H.</author><author>Spindel, Robert C.</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Zarnetske, Michael</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Acoustic remote sensing of large-scale temperature variability in the North Pacific Ocean</title><secondary-title>Gayana (Concepción)</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Gayana (Concepción)</full-title></periodical><pages>576-577</pages><volume>68</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><publisher>Universidad de Concepción.Facultad de Ciencias Naturales y Oceanográficas.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.4067/S0717-65382004000300047</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Worcester et al. - 2004 - Acoustic remote sensing of large-scale temperature variability in the North Pacific Ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.scielo.cl/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0717-65382004000300047&amp;lng=en&amp;nrm=iso&amp;tlng=en</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Krakauer, Nir Y.</author><author>Randerson, James T.</author><author>Primeau, François W.</author><author>Gruber, Nicolas</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Carbon isotope evidence for the latitudinal distribution and wind speed dependence of the air-sea gas transfer velocity</title><secondary-title>Tellus, Series B: Chemical and Physical Meteorology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Tellus, Series B: Chemical and Physical Meteorology</full-title></periodical><pages>390-417</pages><volume>58</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2006</year></dates><isbn>1600-0889</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/j.1600-0889.2006.00223.x</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Krakauer et al. - 2006 - Carbon isotope evidence for the latitudinal distribution and wind speed dependence of the air-sea gas transfer.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The air–sea gas transfer velocity is an important determinant of the exchange of gases, including CO2, between the atmosphere and ocean, but the magnitude of the transfer velocity and what factors control it remains poorly known. Here, we use oceanic and atmospheric observations of 14C and 13C to constrain the global mean gas transfer velocity as well as the exponent of its wind speed dependence, utilizing the distinct signatures left by the air–sea exchange of 14CO2 and 13CO2. While the atmosphere and ocean inventories of 14CO2 and 13CO2 constrain the mean gas transfer velocity, the latitudinal pattern in the atmospheric and oceanic 14C and 13C distributions contain information about the wind speed dependence. We computed the uptake of bomb 14C by the ocean for different transfer velocity patterns using pulse response functions from an ocean general circulation model, and evaluated the match between the predicted bomb 14C concentrations and observationally based estimates for the 1970s–1990s. Using a wind speed climatology based on satellite measurements, we solved either for the best-fit global relationship between gas exchange and mean wind speed or for the mean gas transfer velocity over each of 11 ocean regions. We also compared the predicted consequences of different gas exchange relationships on the rate of change and interhemisphere gradient of 14C in atmospheric CO2 with tree-ring and atmospheric measurements. Our results suggest that globally, the dependence of the air–sea gas transfer velocity on wind speed is close to linear, with an exponent of 0.5 ± 0.4, and that the global mean gas transfer velocity at a Schmidt number of 660 is 20 ± 3 cm/hr, similar to the results of previous analyses. We find that the air–sea flux of 13C estimated from atmosphere and ocean observations also suggests a lower than quadratic dependence of gas exchange on wind speed.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mikaloff Fletcher, Sara E.</author><author>Gruber, Nicolas</author><author>Jacobson, Andrew R.</author><author>Gloor, Manuel</author><author>Doney, S. C.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Gerber, Markus</author><author>Follows, Michael J.</author><author>Joos, F.</author><author>Lindsay, Keith</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mouchet, Anne</author><author>Müller, Simon A.</author><author>Sarmiento, Jorge L.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Inverse estimates of the oceanic sources and sinks of natural CO$_2$ and the implied oceanic carbon transport</title><secondary-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</full-title></periodical><pages>1-19</pages><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2007</year></dates><isbn>0886-6236</isbn><accession-num>18647838</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2006GB002751</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Mikaloff Fletcher et al. - 2007 - Inverse estimates of the oceanic sources and sinks of natural CO$_2$ and the implied oceanic carbon tr.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We use an inverse method to estimate the global-scale pattern of the air-sea flux of natural CO2, i.e., the component of the CO2 flux due to the natural carbon cycle that already existed in preindustrial times, on the basis of ocean interior observations of dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) and other tracers, from which we estimate ΔCgasex, i.e., the component of the observed DIC that is due to the gas exchange of natural CO2. We employ a suite of 10 different Ocean General Circulation Models (OGCMs) to quantify the error arising from uncertainties in the modeled transport required to link the interior ocean observations to the surface fluxes. The results from the contributing OGCMs are weighted using a model skill score based on a comparison of each modelﾒs simulated natural radiocarbon with observations. We find a pattern of air-sea flux of natural CO2 characterized by outgassing in the Southern Ocean between 44°S and 59°S, vigorous uptake at midlatitudes of both hemispheres, and strong outgassing in the tropics. In the Northern Hemisphere and the tropics, the inverse estimates generally agree closely with the natural CO2 flux results from forward simulations of coupled OGCM-biogeochemistry models undertaken as part of the second phase of the Ocean Carbon Model Intercomparison Project (OCMIP-2). The OCMIP-2 simulations find far less air-sea exchange than the inversion south of 20°S, but more recent forward OGCM studies are in better agreement with the inverse estimates in the Southern Hemisphere. The strong source and sink pattern south of 20°S was not apparent in an earlier inversion study, because the choice of region boundaries led to a partial cancellation of the sources and sinks. We show that the inversely estimated flux pattern is clearly traceable to gradients in the observed ΔCgasex, and that it is relatively insensitive to the choice of OGCM or potential biases in ΔCgasex. Our inverse estimates imply a southward interhemispheric transport of 0.31 ± 0.02 Pg C yr-1, most of which occurs in the Atlantic. This is considerably smaller than the 1 Pg C yr-1 of Northern Hemisphere uptake that has been inferred from atmospheric CO2 observations during the 1980s and 1990s, which supports the hypothesis of a Northern Hemisphere terrestrial sink.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Linearization of an oceanic general circulation model for data assimilation and climate studies</title><secondary-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</full-title></periodical><pages>1420-1443</pages><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1997</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/1520-0426(1997)014&lt;1420:LOAOGC&gt;2.0.CO;2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Wunsch - 1997 - Linearization of an oceanic general circulation model for data assimilation and climate studies.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Abstract A recipe for the linearization and state reduction of a general circulation model (GCM) is evaluated in a North Pacific test basin. The underlying assumption is that modern GCMs are, or will become, sufficiently accurate so that large-scale differences with the real ocean are small and have linear physics. Model Green?s functions are used to construct a reduced-order linear model that compares favorably with the large-scale response of the GCM away from the western boundary. In a numerical example, the linear model is applied to the estimation of the large-scale internal structure of a simulated ocean using pseudotomographic and altimetric measurements. The sensitivity of the solution to a priori statistical assumptions is analyzed. Several algorithmic improvements are explored to render the estimation procedure more efficient, more accurate, and easier to implement than in previous studies.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Generic">31</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Webb, Tony</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Send, Uwe</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Basin-scale ocean circulation from combined altimetric, tomographic and model data</title><secondary-title>Nature</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Nature</full-title></periodical><pages>618-621</pages><volume>385</volume><issue>6617</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1997</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1038/385618a0</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis et al. - 1997 - Basin-scale ocean circulation from combined altimetric, tomographic and model data.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/385618a0</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The ocean stores and transports vast quantities of heat, fresh water, carbon and other materials, and its circulation plays an important role in determining both the Earth's climate and fundamental processes in the biosphere, Understanding the development of climate and important biological cycles therefore requires detailed knowledge of ocean circulation and its transport properties, This cannot be achieved solely through modelling, but must involve accurate observations of the spatio-temporal evolution of the global oceanic flow field. Estimates of oceanic flow are currently made on the basis of space-borne measurements of the sea surface, and monitoring of the ocean interior. Satellite altimetry and acoustic tomography are complementary for this purpose(1), as the former provides detailed horizontal coverage of the surface, and the latter the requisite vertical sampling of the interior. High-quality acoustic-tomographic(2) and altimetric(3) data are now available to test the combined power of these technologies for estimating oceanic flows. Here we demonstrate that, with the aid of state-of-the-art numerical models, it is possible to recover from these data a detailed spatio-temporal record of flow over basin-scale volumes of fluid. Our present results are restricted to the Mediterranean Sea, but the method described here provides a powerful tool for studying oceanic circulation worldwide.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Farmer, David M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Path-averaged measurements of turbulence beneath ice in the Arctic</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research</full-title></periodical><pages>13,665-13,663</pages><volume>100</volume><issue>C7</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1995</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Farmer - 1995 - Path-averaged measurements of turbulence beneath ice in the Arctic.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Two-way acoustic propagation measurements obtained along 200-m horizontal paths, a few meters below ice in the eastern Arctic, are used to estimate energy dissipation rate and momentum transfer between the ice and the ocean. Forward scattered sound propagating through the turbulent fluid of the boundary layer under ice produces characteristic scintillation patterns at the receivers which are interpreted in terms of the refractive index fine structure of the flow. l•eciprocal travel time measurements yield information about the velocity variability along each acoustic path. By combining these two types of measurements, the contributions of sound speed and water-particle velocity fluctuations to forward acoustic scatter can be separated. For the particular case of the under-ice boundary layer, sound speed variability is negligible. Therefore, under the assumptions of a Kolmogorov inertial subrange and Taylor's frozen field hypothesis, the one-way and the reciprocal acoustical measurements provide two independent estimates of turbulent kinetic energy dissipation rate averaged over the propagation paths. Both these methods yield a value of 8 x 10 -8 W kg -1 6 m from the bottom of the ice for a 7-hour period during which the mean ice-relative velocity is 0.11 m s -1. Surface layer approximations then yield a value of 0.03 N m -2 for turbulent stress near the surface. The acoustical measurements also indicate that circulation around ice keels can cause horizontal &quot;lift forces&quot; of order 104 N.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gross, Richard S.</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Atmospheric and oceanic excitation of length-of-day variations during 1980–2000</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research B: Solid Earth</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research B: Solid Earth</full-title></periodical><volume>109</volume><issue>B1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2003JB002432</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gross, Fukumori, Menemenlis - 2004 - Atmospheric and oceanic excitation of length-of-day variations during 1980–2000.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Although nontidal changes in the Earth’s length-of-day on timescales of a few days to a few years are primarily caused by changes in the angular momentum of the zonal winds, other processes can be expected to cause the length-of-day to change as well. Here the relative contribution of upper atmospheric winds, surface pressure, oceanic currents, and ocean-bottom pressure to changing the length-of-day during 1980–2000 is evaluated using estimates of atmospheric angular momentum from the National Centers for Environmental Prediction/National Center for Atmospheric Research reanalysis project, estimates of the angular momentum of the zonal winds in the upper atmosphere from the United Kingdom Meteorological Office, and estimates of oceanic angular momentum from the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean consortium’s simulation of the general circulation of the oceans. On intraseasonal timescales, atmospheric surface pressure, oceanic currents, and ocean-bottom pressure are found to be about equally important in causing the length-of-day to change, while upper atmospheric winds are found to be less important than these mechanisms. On seasonal timescales, the upper atmospheric winds are more important than the sum of currents and bottom pressure in causing the length-of-day to change and, except at the annual frequency, are even more important than surface pressure changes. On interannual timescales, oceanic currents and ocean-bottom pressure are found to be only marginally effective in causing the length-ofday to change.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fieguth, Paul W.</author><author>Willsky, Alan S.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A general multiresolution approach to the estimation of dense fields in remote sensing</title><secondary-title>ICIP'96: 1996 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>ICIP'96: 1996 IEEE International Conference on Image Processing</full-title></periodical><pages>609-612</pages><volume>2</volume><keywords/><dates><year>1996</year></dates><isbn>078033258X</isbn><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fieguth et al. - 1996 - A general multiresolution approach to the estimation of dense fields in remote sensing.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A fast multiscale optimal interpolation algorithm has been adapted to the mapping of hydrographic and other oceanographic data. This multiscale algorithm produces solution and error estimates which are consistent with those obtained from exact least-squares methods, but at a small fraction of the computational cost. Problems whose solution would be completely impractical using exact least-squares, that is problems with tens or hundreds of thousands of measurements and estimation grid points, can easily be solved on a small workstation using the multiscale algorithm. Contrary to methods previously proposed for solving large least-squares problems, the multiscale approach provides error statistics while permitting long-range correlations, using all measurements, and permitting arbitrary measurement locations. A set of MATLAB-callable routines which implements the multiscale algorithm and reproduces the results obtained in this paper are available by anonymous FTP; see the last section of this paper for details.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A Near-Uniform Basin-Wide Sea Level Fluctuation of the Mediterranean Sea</title><secondary-title>Journal of physical oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of physical oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>338-358</pages><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2007</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/JPO3016.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fukumori, Menemenlis - 2007 - A Near-Uniform Basin-Wide Sea Level Fluctuation of the Mediterranean Sea.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A new basin-wide oscillation of the Mediterranean Sea is identified and analyzed using sea level obser-vations from the Ocean Topography Experiment (TOPEX)/Poseidon satellite altimeter and a numerical ocean circulation model. More than 50% of the large-scale, nontidal, and non-pressure-driven variance of sea level can be attributed to this oscillation, which is nearly uniform in phase and amplitude across the entire basin. The oscillation has periods ranging from 10 days to several years and has a magnitude as large as 10 cm. The model suggests that the fluctuations are driven by winds at the Strait of Gibraltar and its neighboring region, including the Alboran Sea and a part of the Atlantic Ocean immediately to the west of the strait. Winds in this region force a net mass flux through the Strait of Gibraltar to which the Mediter-ranean Sea adjusts almost uniformly across its entire basin with depth-independent pressure perturbations. The wind-driven response can be explained in part by wind setup; a near-stationary balance is established between the along-strait wind in this forcing region and the sea level difference between the Mediterranean Sea and the Atlantic Ocean. The amplitude of this basin-wide wind-driven sea level fluctuation is inversely proportional to the setup region's depth but is insensitive to its width including that of Gibraltar Strait. The wind-driven fluctuation is coherent with atmospheric pressure over the basin and contributes to the appar-ent deviation of the Mediterranean Sea from an inverse barometer response.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fieguth, Paul W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Ho, T.</author><author>Willsky, Alan S.</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mapping mediterranean altimeter data with a multiresolution optimalinterpolation algorithm</title><secondary-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</full-title></periodical><pages>535-546</pages><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1998</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/1520-0426(1998)015&lt;0535:MMADWA&gt;2.0.CO;2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fieguth et al. - 1998 - Mapping mediterranean altimeter data with a multiresolution optimalinterpolation algorithm.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Abstract A multiresolution optimal interpolation scheme is described and used to map the sea level anomaly of the Mediterranean Sea based on TOPEX/Poseidon and ERS-1 data. The principal advantages of the multiresolution scheme are its high computational efficiency, the requirement for explicit statistical models for the oceanographic signal and the measurement errors, and the production of error variances for all estimates at multiple scales. A set of Matlab-callable routines that implement the multiresolution scheme have been made available via anonymous FTP. The oceanographic signal is here modeled as a stationary 1/k? process, where k is the horizontal wavenumber. Measurement noise is modeled as the sum of two separate random processes: a Gaussian white noise process and a correlated process of a low wavenumber representing the uncertainties in the orbital position of the satellite and in the atmospheric load corrections. The efficiency of the multiresolution scheme allowed the testing of more than 16000 sets of hypothesized statistical prior model parameters to determine the most likely parameters. Mapping results with and without low wavenumber error corrections are presented and compared.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mikaloff Fletcher, Sara E.</author><author>Gruber, Nicolas</author><author>Jacobson, Andrew R.</author><author>Doney, Scott C.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Gerber, Markus</author><author>Follows, Michael J.</author><author>Joos, Fortunat</author><author>Lindsay, Keith</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mouchet, Anne</author><author>Müller, Simon A.</author><author>Sarmiento, Jorge L.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Inverse estimates of anthropogenic CO$_2$ uptake, transport, and storage by the ocean</title><secondary-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</full-title></periodical><pages>1-16</pages><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2006</year></dates><isbn>08866236</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2005GB002530</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Mikaloff Fletcher et al. - 2006 - Inverse estimates of anthropogenic CO$_2$ uptake, transport, and storage by the ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1029/2005GB002530</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Regional air-sea fluxes of anthropogenic CO2 are estimated using a Green’s function inversion method that combines data-based estimates of anthropogenic CO2 in the ocean with information about ocean transport and mixing from a suite of Ocean General Circulation Models (OGCMs). In order to quantify the uncertainty associated with the estimated fluxes owing to modeled transport and errors in the data, we employ 10 OGCMs and three scenarios representing biases in the data-based anthropogenic CO2 estimates. On the basis of the prescribed anthropogenic CO2 storage, we find a global uptake of 2.2 ± 0.25 Pg C yr-1, scaled to 1995. This error estimate represents the standard deviation of the models weighted by a CFC-based model skill score, which reduces the error range and emphasizes those models that have been shown to reproduce observed tracer concentrations most accurately. The greatest anthropogenic CO2 uptake occurs in the Southern Ocean and in the tropics. The flux estimates imply vigorous northward transport in the Southern Hemisphere, northward cross-equatorial transport, and equatorward transport at high northern latitudes. Compared with forward simulations, we find substantially more uptake in the Southern Ocean, less uptake in the Pacific Ocean, and less global uptake. The large-scale spatial pattern of the estimated flux is generally insensitive to possible biases in the data and the models employed. However, the global uptake scales approximately linearly with changes in the global anthropogenic CO2 inventory. Considerable uncertainties remain in some regions, particularly the Southern Ocean.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Campin, Jean-Michel</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Nguyen, An T.</author><author>Schodlok, Michael P.</author><author>Zhang, Hong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>ECCO2: High resolution global ocean and sea ice data synthesis</title><secondary-title>Mercator Ocean Quarterly Newsletter</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Mercator Ocean Quarterly Newsletter</full-title></periodical><pages>13-21</pages><volume>31</volume><issue>October</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2008</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis et al. - 2008 - ECCO2 High resolution global ocean and sea ice data synthesis.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.mercator-ocean.fr/content/download/691/5904/version/1/file/lettre_31_en.pdf#page=13</url></web-urls></urls><label>CMS</label><abstract>The Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO) project was established in 1998 as part of the World Ocean Circulation Experiment (WOCE) with the goal of combining a general circulation model (GCM) with diverse observations in order to produce a quantitative depiction of the time-evolving global ocean state. Such combinations, also known as data assimilation, are important because available remotely sensed and in-situ observations are sparse and incomplete compared to the scales and properties of ocean circulation. These combinations also provide rigorous consistency tests for models and for data. In contrast to numerical weather prediction that also combines models and data, ECCO estimates are physically consistent; in particular, ECCO estimates do not contain discontinuities when and where data are ingested. First generation ECCO solutions are available and widely used for numerous science applications but the coarse horizontal grid spacing and the lack of Arctic Ocean and of sea ice of these first-generation solutions limits their ability to describe the real ocean. To address these shortcomings, the follow-on ECCO, Phase II (ECCO2) project aims to produce a best-possible, global, time-evolving synthesis of most available ocean and sea-ice data at a resolution that admits ocean eddies. A first ECCO2 synthesis for the period 1992– 2007 has been obtained using a Green's Function approach (Menemenlis, et al., 2005a) to estimate initial temperature and salinity conditions, surface boundary conditions, and several empirical ocean and sea ice model parameters. Data constraints include altimetry, gravity, drifter, hydrography, and observations of sea-ice. A large complement of high-frequency and high- resolution diagnostics has been saved; these diagnostics are made available to the scientific community via ftp and OPeNDAP servers at   applications</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Cazes-Boezio, Gabriel</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mechoso, Carlos R.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Impact of ECCO ocean-state estimates on the initialization of seasonal climate forecasts</title><secondary-title>Journal of Climate</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Climate</full-title></periodical><pages>1929-1947</pages><volume>21</volume><issue>9</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2008</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/2007JCLI1574.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Cazes-Boezio, Menemenlis, Mechoso - 2008 - Impact of ECCO ocean-state estimates on the initialization of seasonal climate forecasts.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The impact of ocean-state estimates generated by the consortium for Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO) on the initialization of a coupled general circulation model (CGCM) for seasonal climate forecasts is examined. The CGCM consists of the University of California, Los Angeles, Atmospheric GCM (UCLA AGCM) and an ECCO ocean configuration of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology GCM (MITgcm). The forecasts correspond to ensemble seasonal hindcasts for the period 1993-2001. For the forecasts, the ocean component of the CGCM is initialized in either early March or in early June using ocean states provided either by an unconstrained forward ocean integration of the MITgcm (the &quot;baseline&quot; hindcasts) or by data-constrained ECCO results (the &quot;ECCO&quot; hindcasts). Forecast skill for both the baseline and the ECCO hindcasts is significantly higher than persistence and compares well with the skill of other state-of-the art CGCM forecast systems. For March initial conditions, the standard errors of sea surface temperature (SST) anomalies in ECCO hindcasts (relative to observed anomalies) are up to 1 C smaller than in the baseline hindcasts over the central and eastern equatorial Pacific (150 degrees-120 degrees W). For June initial conditions, the errors of ECCO hindcasts are up to 0.5 degrees C smaller than in the baseline hindcasts. The smaller standard error of the ECCO hindcasts is, in part, due to a more realistic equatorial thermocline structure of the ECCO initial conditions. This study confirms the value of physically consistent ocean-state estimation for the initialization of seasonal climate forecasts.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Losch, Martin</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Campin, Jean-Michel</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>On the formulation of sea-ice models. Part 1: Effects of different solver implementations and parameterizations</title><secondary-title>Ocean Modelling</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Ocean Modelling</full-title></periodical><pages>129-144</pages><volume>33</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Adjoint modeling</keyword><keyword>Canadian arctic archipelago</keyword><keyword>Coupled ocean and sea ice model</keyword><keyword>EVP</keyword><keyword>Numerical sea ice modeling</keyword><keyword>Sea-ice export</keyword><keyword>Sensitivities</keyword><keyword>State estimation</keyword><keyword>Viscous-plastic rheology</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2010</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><isbn>1463-5003</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.ocemod.2009.12.008</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Losch et al. - 2010 - On the formulation of sea-ice models. Part 1 Effects of different solver implementations and parameterizations.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ocemod.2009.12.008</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>This paper describes the sea ice component of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm); it presents example Arctic and Antarctic results from a realistic, eddy-admitting, global ocean and sea ice configuration; and it compares B-grid and C-grid dynamic solvers and other numerical details of the parameterized dynamics and thermodynamics in a regional Arctic configuration. Ice mechanics follow a viscous-plastic rheology and the ice momentum equations are solved numerically using either line-successive-over-relaxation (LSOR) or elastic-viscous-plastic (EVP) dynamic models. Ice thermodynamics are represented using either a zero-heat-capacity formulation or a two-layer formulation that conserves enthalpy. The model includes prognostic variables for snow thickness and for sea ice salinity. The above sea ice model components were borrowed from current generation climate models but they were reformulated on an Arakawa C grid in order to match the MITgcm oceanic grid and they were modified in many ways to permit efficient and accurate automatic differentiation. Both stress tensor divergence and advective terms are discretized with the finite-volume method. The choice of the dynamic solver has a considerable effect on the solution; this effect can be larger than, for example, the choice of lateral boundary conditions, of ice rheology, and of ice-ocean stress coupling. The solutions obtained with different dynamic solvers typically differ by a few cms-1 in ice drift speeds, 50cm in ice thickness, and order 200km3yr-1 in freshwater (ice and snow) export out of the Arctic. © 2010 Elsevier Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Fieguth, Paul W.</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Willsky, Alan S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Adaptation of a fast optimal interpolation algorithm to the mapping of oceanographic data</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research C: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research C: Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>10573-10584</pages><volume>102</volume><issue>C5</issue><keywords><keyword>doi:10.1029/97JC00697</keyword><keyword>http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/97JC00697</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1997</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/97JC00697</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis et al. - 1997 - Adaptation of a fast optimal interpolation algorithm to the mapping of oceanographic data.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A fast, recently developed, multiscale optimal interpolation algorithm has been adapted to the mapping of hydrographic and other oceanographic data. This algorithm produces solution and error estimates which are consistent with those obtained from exact least squares methods, but at a small fraction of the computational cost. Problems whose solution would be completely impractical using exact least squares, that is, problems with tens or hundreds of thousands of measurements and estimation grid points, can easily be solved on a small workstation using the multiscale algorithm. In contrast to methods previously proposed for solving large least squares problems, our approach provides estimation error statistics while permitting long-range correlations, using all measurements, and permitting arbitrary measurement locations. The multiscale algorithm itself, published elsewhere, is not the focus of this paper. However, the algorithm requires statistical models having a very particular multiscale structure; it is the development of a class of multiscale statistical models, appropriate for oceanographic mapping problems, with which we concern ourselves in this paper. The approach is illustrated by mapping temperature in the northeastern Pacific. The number of hydrographic stations is kept deliberately small to show that multiscale and exact least squares results are comparable. A portion of the data were not used in the analysis; these data serve to test the multiscale estimates. A major advantage of the present approach is the ability to repeat the estimation procedure a large number of times for sensitivity studies, parameter estimation, and model testing. We have made available by anonymous Ftp a set of MATLAB-callable routines which implement the multiscale algorithm and the statistical models developed in this paper.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Condron, Alan</author><author>Winsor, Peter</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Simulated response of the Arctic freshwater budget to extreme NAO wind forcing</title><secondary-title>Journal of Climate</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Climate</full-title></periodical><pages>2422-2437</pages><volume>22</volume><issue>9</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><isbn>0894-8755</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/2008JCLI2626.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Condron et al. - 2009 - Simulated response of the Arctic freshwater budget to extreme NAO wind forcing.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The authors investigate the response of the Arctic Ocean freshwater\nbudget to changes in the North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO) using a\nregional-ocean configuration of the Massachusetts Institute of\nTechnology GCM (MITgcm) and carry out several different 10-yr and 30-yr\nintegrations. At 1/6 degrees (similar to 18 km) resolution the model\nresolves the major Arctic transport pathways, including Bering Strait\nand the Canadian Archipelago. Two main calculations are performed by\nrepeating the wind fields of two contrasting NAO years in each run for\nthe extreme negative and positive NAO phases of 1969 and 1989,\nrespectively. These calculations are compared both with a control run\nand the compiled observationally based freshwater budget estimate of\nSerreze et al.\nThe results show a clear response in the Arctic freshwater budget to NAO\nforcing, that is, repeat NAO negative wind forcing results in virtually\nall freshwater being retained in the Arctic, with the bulk of the\nfreshwater content being pooled in the Beaufort gyre. In contrast,\nrepeat NAO positive forcing accelerates the export of freshwater out of\nthe Arctic to the North Atlantic, primarily via Fram Strait (similar to\n900 km(3) yr(-1)) and the Canadian Archipelago (similar to 500 km(3)\nyr(-1)), with a total loss in freshwater storage of similar to 13 000\nkm(3) (15%) after 10 yr. The large increase in freshwater export\nthrough the Canadian Archipelago highlights the important role that this\ngateway plays in redistributing the freshwater of the Arctic to subpolar\nseas, by providing a direct pathway from the Arctic basin to the\nLabrador Sea, Gulf Stream system, and Atlantic Ocean. The authors\ndiscuss the sensitivity of the Arctic Ocean to long-term fixed extreme\nNAO states and show that the freshwater content of the Arctic is able to\nbe restored to initial values from a depleted freshwater state after\nsimilar to 20 yr.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Reynolds, Richard W.</author><author>Chelton, Dudley B.</author><author>Roberts-Jones, Jonah</author><author>Martin, Matthew J.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Merchant, Christopher John</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Objective determination of feature resolution in two sea surface temperature analyses</title><secondary-title>Journal of Climate</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Climate</full-title></periodical><pages>2514-2533</pages><volume>26</volume><issue>8</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2013</year></dates><isbn>0894-8755</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/JCLI-D-12-00787.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Reynolds et al. - 2013 - Objective determination of feature resolution in two sea surface temperature analyses.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Considerable effort is presently being devoted to producing high-resolution sea surface temperature (SST) analyses with a goal of spatial grid resolutions as low as 1 km. Because grid resolution is not the same as feature resolution, a method is needed to objectively determine the resolution capability and accuracy of SST analysis products. Ocean model SST fields are used in this study as simulated “true” SST data and subsampled based on actual infrared and microwave satellite data coverage. The subsampled data are used to simulate sampling errors due to missing data. Two different SST analyses are considered and run using both the full and the subsampled model SST fields, with and without additional noise. The results are compared as a function of spatial scales of variability using wavenumber auto- and cross-spectral analysis. The spectral variance at high wavenumbers (smallest wavelengths) is shown to be attenuated relative to the true SST because of smoothing that is inherent to both analysis procedures. Comparisons of the two analyses (both having grid sizes of roughly 1/20 degree) show important differences. One analysis tends to reproduce small-scale features more accurately when the high-resolution data coverage is good but produces more spurious small-scale noise when the high-resolution data coverage is poor. Analysis procedures can thus generate small-scale features with and without data, but the small-scale features in an SST analysis may be just noise when high-resolution data are sparse. Users must therefore be skeptical of high-resolution SST products, especially in regions where high-resolution (~5 km) infrared satellite data are limited because of cloud cover.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Davis, Xujing Jia</author><author>Rothstein, Lewis M.</author><author>Dewar, William K.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Numerical investigations of seasonal and interannual variability of North Pacific subtropical mode water and its implications for Pacific climate variability</title><secondary-title>Journal of Climate</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Climate</full-title></periodical><pages>2648-2665</pages><volume>24</volume><issue>11</issue><keywords><keyword>Climate variability</keyword><keyword>Interannual variability</keyword><keyword>North Pacific Ocean</keyword><keyword>Pacific decadal oscillation</keyword><keyword>Seasonal variability</keyword><keyword>Subtropics</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2011</year></dates><isbn>0894-8755</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/2010JCLI3435.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Davis et al. - 2011 - Numerical investigations of seasonal and interannual variability of North Pacific subtropical mode water and its i.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>North Pacific Subtropical Mode Water (NPSTMW) is an essential feature of the North Pacific subtropical gyre imparting significant influence on regional SST evolution on seasonal and longer time scales and, as such, is an important component of basin-scale North Pacific climate variability. This study examines the seasonal-to-interannual variability of NPSTMW, the physical processes responsible for this variability, and the connections between NPSTMW and basin-scale climate signals using an eddy-permitting 1979-2006 ocean simulation made available by the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean, Phase II (ECCO2). The monthly mean seasonal cycle of NPSTMW in the simulation exhibits three distinct phases: (i) formation during November March, (ii) isolation during March June, and (iii) dissipation during June November each corresponding to significant changes in upper-ocean structure. An interannual signal is also evident in NPSTMW volume and other characteristic properties with volume minima occurring in 1979, 1988, and 1999. This volume variability is correlated with the Pacific decadal oscillation (PDO) with zero time lag. Further analyses demonstrate the connection of NPSTMW to the basin-scale ocean circulation. With this, modulations of upper-ocean structure driven by the varying strength and position of the westerlies as well as the regional air sea heat flux pattern are seen to contribute to the variability of NPSTMW volume on interannual time scales.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Gould, John</author><author>Bold, G.</author><author>Chiu, C.-S.</author><author>Colosi, J. A.</author><author>Cornuelle, Bruce D.</author><author>Desaubies, Yves</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Forbes, Andrew M. G.</author><author>Gaillard, Fabienne</author><author>Gavrilov, A.</author><author>Howe, Bruce M.</author><author>Lawrence, M.</author><author>Lynch, James F.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mercer, James A.</author><author>Mikhalevsky, Peter N.</author><author>Munk, Walter H.</author><author>Nakano, I.</author><author>Schott, Friedrich</author><author>Send, Uwe</author><author>Spindel, Robert C.</author><author>Terre, T.</author><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Observing the ocean in the 2000s: a strategy for the role of acoustic tomography in ocean climate observation</title><secondary-title>Observing the Oceans in the 21st Century</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Observing the Oceans in the 21st Century</full-title></periodical><pages>391-418</pages><issue>September 1999</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2001</year></dates><isbn>0642706182 9780642706188</isbn><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dushaw et al. - 2001 - Observing the ocean in the 2000s a strategy for the role of acoustic tomography in ocean climate observation.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://eprints.uni-kiel.de/675/%5Cnhttp://eprints.soton.ac.uk/55453/</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>n/a</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>ATOC Consortium</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ocean climate change: Comparison of acoustic tomography, satellite altimetry, and modeling</title><secondary-title>Science (New York, N.Y.)</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science (New York, N.Y.)</full-title></periodical><pages>1327-1332</pages><volume>281</volume><issue>5381</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1998</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://ATOC Consortium - 1998 - Ocean climate change Comparison of acoustic tomography, satellite altimetry, and modeling.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.cheric.org/research/tech/periodicals/view.php?seq=259871%5Cnpapers2://publication/uuid/C2575E0F-CE2C-45DD-9751-3A77199B1F28</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Comparisons of gyre-scale acoustic and direct thermal measurements of heat content in the Pacific Ocean, satellite altimeter measurements of sea surface height, and results from a general circulation model show that only about half of the seasonal and year-to-year changes in sea level are attributable to thermal expansion. Interpreting climate change signals from fluctuations in sea level is therefore complicated. The annual cycle of heat flux is 150 ± 25 watts per square meter (peak-to-peak, corresponding to a 0.2°C vertically averaged temperature cycle); an interannual change of similar magnitude is also detected. Meteorological estimates of surface heat flux, if accurate, require a large seasonal cycle in the advective heat flux.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Adcroft, Alistair J.</author><author>Campin, Jean-Michel</author><author>Cheng, Benny</author><author>Ciotti, Robert B.</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Henze, Christopher E.</author><author>Köhl, Armin</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Taft, J.</author><author>Zhang, J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>NASA supercomputer improves prospects for ocean climate research</title><secondary-title>EOS Transactions AGU</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>EOS Transactions AGU</full-title></periodical><pages>89-96</pages><volume>86</volume><issue>9</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2005</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2005EO090002</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis et al. - 2005 - NASA supercomputer improves prospects for ocean climate research.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Halpern, David</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Wang, Xiaochun</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Impact of data assimilation on ECCO2 equatorial undercurrent and North equatorial countercurrent in the Pacific Ocean</title><secondary-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</full-title></periodical><pages>131-143</pages><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/JTECH-D-14-00025.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Halpern, Menemenlis, Wang - 2015 - Impact of data assimilation on ECCO2 equatorial undercurrent and North equatorial countercurrent in t.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The impact of data assimilation on the transports of eastward-flowing Equatorial Undercurrent (EUC) and North Equatorial Countercurrent (NECC) in the Pacific Ocean from 1458E to958Wduring 2004-05 and 2009-11 was assessed. Two Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean, Phase II (ECCO2), solutions were analyzed: one with data assimilation and one without. Assimilated data included satellite observations of sea surface temperature and ocean surface topography, in which the sampling patterns were approximately uniform over the 5 years, and in situ measurements of subsurface salinity and temperature profiles, in which the sampling patterns varied considerably in space and time throughout the 5 years. Velocity measurements were not assimilated. The impact of data assimilation was considered significant when the difference between the transports computed with and without data assimilation was greater than 5.5 × 106m3 s-1 (or 5.5 Sv; 1 Sv ≡ 106m3 s-1) for the EUC and greater than 5.0 Sv for the NECC. In addition, the difference of annual-mean transports computed from 3-day-averaged data was statistically significant at the 95%level. The impact of data assimilation ranged from no impact to very substantial impact when data assimilation increased the EUC transport and decreased the NECC transport. The study's EUC results had some correspondence with other studies and no simple agreement or disagreement pattern emerged among all studies of the impact of data assimilation. No comparable study of the impact of data assimilation on the NECC has been made.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Zhang, Hong</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Campin, Jean-Michel</author><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Losch, Martin</author><author>Nguyen, An T.</author><author>Schodlok, Michael P.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Global ocean and sea ice state estimation in the presence of eddies</title></titles><periodical/><pages>3-5</pages><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis et al. - 2009 - Global ocean and sea ice state estimation in the presence of eddies.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We aim to demonstrate the feasibility and utility of global, eddying ocean and sea ice state estimation. A first synthesis for the period 1992-2002 has been obtained using a Green's functions approach. Data constraints include hydrography, altimetry, gravity, drifter, and observations of sea-ice. Although the control space is small (~80 parameters), this first globalocean and sea ice data synthesis substantially reduces large-scale biases and drifts of the model relative to observations and to the baseline integration. A second synthesis is being obtained during the ARGO-rich period using the adjoint method, which permits a much larger number of control parameters to be estimated.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Ponte, Rui M.</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Balmaseda, Magdalena Alonso</author><author>Awaji, Toshiyuki</author><author>Baehr, J.</author><author>Behringer, D.</author><author>Carton, J.</author><author>Ferry, Nicolas</author><author>Fischer, A.</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Giese, Benjamin</author><author>Haines, K.</author><author>Harrison, E.</author><author>Hernandez, F.</author><author>Kamachi, M.</author><author>Keppenne, C.</author><author>Köhl, Armin</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Oke, P.</author><author>Remy, Elisabeth</author><author>Rienecker, Michele M.</author><author>Rosati, A.</author><author>Smith, Doug</author><author>Speer, K.</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Weaver, A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Observational Requirements for Global-Scale Ocean Climate Analysis: Lessons from Ocean State Estimation</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of OceanObs'09: Sustained Ocean Observations and Information for Society</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of OceanObs'09: Sustained Ocean Observations and Information for Society</full-title></periodical><pages>459-471</pages><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2010</year></dates><isbn>978-3-86987-200-1</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.5270/OceanObs09.cwp.42</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Heimbach et al. - 2010 - Observational Requirements for Global-Scale Ocean Climate Analysis Lessons from Ocean State Estimation.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.oceanobs09.net/proceedings/cwp/cwp42</url></web-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Awaji, Toshiyuki</author><author>Balmaseda, Magdalena Alonso</author><author>Behringer, D.</author><author>Carton, J.</author><author>Ferry, Nicolas</author><author>Fischer, A.</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Giese, Benjamin</author><author>Haines, K.</author><author>Harrison, E.</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Kamachi, M.</author><author>Keppenne, C.</author><author>Masina, S</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Ponte, Rui M.</author><author>Remy, Elisabeth</author><author>Rienecker, Michele M.</author><author>Rosati, A.</author><author>Weaver, A</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Xue, Y</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ocean information provided through ensemble ocean syntheses</title></titles><periodical/><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Stammer et al. - 2009 - Ocean information provided through ensemble ocean syntheses.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Awaji, Toshiyuki</author><author>Balmaseda, Magdalena Alonso</author><author>Greiner, Eric</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ocean State Estimation for Climate Research</title><secondary-title>Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>160-167</pages><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><isbn>978-3-86987-200-1</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.5670/oceanog.2009.74</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Lee et al. - 2009 - Ocean State Estimation for Climate Research.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Spurred by the development of satellite and in situ observing systems, global ocean state estimation has flourished in the past decade. Today, a suite of global ocean state estimates has been generated and is being applied to studies over a wide range of subjects in physical oceanography and climate research as well as other disciplines. This paper highlights some examples Of using ocean state estimations for ocean and climate research. Many assimilation groups from different countries participated in a Climate Variability and Predictability program/Global Ocean Data Assimilation Experiment global ocean reanalysis evaluation effort in which intercomparisons were performed for a suite of diagnostic quantities and indices, including evaluations against observations. Examples of the intercomparisons are presented to highlight the consistencies and uncertainties of the estimation products and to examine the ability of these products to detect climate signals. Future challenges for state estimation for climate applications are also discussed.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Others, 35</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A global ocean acoustic observing network</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of OceanObs'09: Sustained Ocean Observations and Information for Society. Venice, Italy, 21-25 September 2009</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of OceanObs'09: Sustained Ocean Observations and Information for Society. Venice, Italy, 21-25 September 2009</full-title></periodical><volume>2</volume><issue>October 2016</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2010</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dushaw, Others - 2010 - A global ocean acoustic observing network.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The ocean is largely transparent to sound, but opaque to electromagnetic radiation. Underwater sound is therefore a powerful tool for remote sensing of the ocean interior. Acoustic measurements can be made either passively, using sound generated by nature, or actively, using sound generated by sources engineered to produce optimal acoustic signals. Both approaches have techniques that are well established and suitable for immediate deployment as part of an operational observing system. Passive acoustics can be employed for a variety of purposes, such as: tracking, counting and studying the behavior of vocalizing marine mammals and fish; assessing and monitoring the ecological impacts of ocean warming and acidification on marine ecosystems and biodiversity; detecting undersea explosions such as nuclear tests or blast fishing; detecting and quantifying tsunamis; measuring rainfall; measuring the properties of undersea earthquakes and volcanoes; monitoring the sound produced by high latitude sea ice; and monitoring anthropogenic activities in marine protected areas. With a modest set of acoustic sources with known locations and accurate timekeeping, the precise locations of underwater instruments and mobile platforms can be determined by triangulation. Such an underwater tracking system can provide the position, navigation, and timekeeping for undersea use that GPS presently provides for terrestrial and space use. Similar or the same acoustic sources can also be used for ocean acoustic tomography. Acoustic tomography is now well established, and the approach was accepted as part of the ocean observing system during OceanObs'99 and OceanObs'09. The acoustic travel times are inherently spatially integrating, naturally suppressing mesoscale variability and providing precise range-averaged temperature and current. They provide a subsurface measurement of temperature; salinity contributes negligibly. Tomographic measurements extend into the abyssal ocean and can be made in ice-covered regions. The measurement can be made without risk of calibration drift - time is the fundamental measurement. Tomographic measurements are nearly instantaneous (a measurement of an ocean basin in an hour) and can be made at any sampling rate (increased sampling adds essentially no additional cost). Because of the integral nature of the data, tomography is best employed in conjunction with numerical ocean models and data assimilation. A decade of measurements (1996-2006) of basin-scale temperature using acoustic thermometry have been completed in the North Pacific Ocean, demonstrating the uniqueness and sustainability of the acoustical measurements. The conclusion is that as ocean observing systems are designed and implemented over the next 20 years, passive and active acoustic sensors serve a multitude of purposes and should be included as integral components.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rocha, Cesar B.</author><author>Chereskin, Teresa K.</author><author>Gille, Sarah T.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mesoscale to submesoscale wavenumber spectra in Drake Passage</title><secondary-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>601-620</pages><volume>46</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Atm/Ocean Structure/ Phenomena</keyword><keyword>Eddies</keyword><keyword>Observational techniques and algorithms</keyword><keyword>Oceanic mixed layer</keyword><keyword>Satellite observations</keyword><keyword>Ship observations</keyword><keyword>Tides</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/JPO-D-15-0087.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Rocha et al. - 2016 - Mesoscale to submesoscale wavenumber spectra in Drake Passage.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/10.1175/JPO-D-15-0087.1</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>AbstractThis study discusses the upper-ocean (0–200 m) horizontal wavenumber spectra in the Drake Passage from 13 yr of shipboard ADCP measurements, altimeter data, and a high-resolution numerical simulation. At scales between 10 and 200 km, the ADCP kinetic energy spectra approximately follow a k−3 power law. The observed flows are more energetic at the surface, but the shape of the kinetic energy spectra is independent of depth. These characteristics resemble predictions of isotropic interior quasigeostrophic turbulence. The ratio of across-track to along-track kinetic energy spectra, however, significantly departs from the expectation of isotropic interior quasigeostrophic turbulence. The inconsistency is dramatic at scales smaller than 40 km. A Helmholtz decomposition of the ADCP spectra and analyses of synthetic and numerical model data show that horizontally divergent, ageostrophic flows account for the discrepancy between the observed spectra and predictions of isotropic interior quasigeostrophic t...</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Ponte, Rui M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO): Advancing CLIVAR Science</title><secondary-title>CLIVAR Exchanges</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>CLIVAR Exchanges</full-title></periodical><pages>41-45</pages><volume>67</volume><issue>19</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2015</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Forget et al. - 2015 - Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO) Advancing CLIVAR Science.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><label>CMS</label></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Manizza, Manfredi</author><author>Follows, Michael J.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>McClelland, James W.</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Peterson, B. J.</author><author>Key, Robert M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A model of the Arctic Ocean carbon cycle</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>1-19</pages><volume>116</volume><issue>12</issue><keywords><keyword>0414</keyword><keyword>0428 Biogeosciences: Carbon cycling (4806)</keyword><keyword>0793 Cryosphere: Biogeochemistry (0412</keyword><keyword>1615</keyword><keyword>4207 Oceanography: General: Arctic and Antarctic o</keyword><keyword>4805 Oceanography: Biological and Chemical: Biogeo</keyword><keyword>4820 Oceanography: Biological and Chemical: Gases</keyword><keyword>DISSOLVED ORGANIC-MATTE</keyword><keyword>GENERAL-CIRCULATION-MODEL</keyword><keyword>air-sea gas exchange</keyword><keyword>biogeochemical cycles</keyword><keyword>land-ocean coupling</keyword><keyword>numerical modeling</keyword><keyword>ocean carbon cycle</keyword><keyword>polar oceans</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2011</year></dates><isbn>2156-2202</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2011JC006998</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Manizza et al. - 2011 - A model of the Arctic Ocean carbon cycle.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2011JC006998</url><url>//wos</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>A three dimensional model of Arctic Ocean circulation and mixing, with a horizontal resolution of 18 km, is overlain by a biogeochemical model resolving the physical, chemical and biological transport and transformations of phosphorus, alkalinity, oxygen and carbon, including the air-sea exchange of dissolved gases and the riverine delivery of dissolved organic carbon. The model qualitatively captures the observed regional and seasonal trends in surface ocean PO4, dissolved inorganic carbon, total alkalinity, and pCO2. Integrated annually, over the basin, the model suggests a net annual uptake of 59 Tg C a−1, within the range of published estimates based on the extrapolation of local observations (20–199 Tg C a−1). This flux is attributable to the cooling (increasing solubility) of waters moving into the basin, mainly from the subpolar North Atlantic. The air-sea flux is regulated seasonally and regionally by sea-ice cover, which modulates both air-sea gas transfer and the photosynthetic production of organic matter, and by the delivery of riverine dissolved organic carbon (RDOC), which drive the regional contrasts in pCO2 between Eurasian and North American coastal waters. Integrated over the basin, the delivery and remineralization of RDOC reduces the net oceanic CO2 uptake by ∼10%.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Manizza, Manfredi</author><author>Follows, Michael J.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>McClelland, James W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Townsend-Small, A.</author><author>Peterson, B. J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Modeling transport and fate of riverine dissolved organic carbon in the Arctic Ocean</title><secondary-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</full-title></periodical><pages>GB4006</pages><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords><keyword>Arctic Ocean</keyword><keyword>biogeochemical processes</keyword><keyword>ocean circulation</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2009</year></dates><isbn>0886-6236</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2008GB003396</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Manizza et al. - 2009 - Modeling transport and fate of riverine dissolved organic carbon in the Arctic Ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://www.agu.org/pubs/crossref/2009/2008GB003396.shtml</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The spatial distribution and fate of riverine dissolved organic carbon (DOC) in the Arctic may be significant for the regional carbon cycle but are difficult to fully characterize using the sparse observations alone. Numerical models of the circulation and biogeochemical cycles of the region can help to interpret and extrapolate the data and may ultimately be applied in global change sensitivity studies. Here we develop and explore a regional, three-dimensional model of the Arctic Ocean in which, for the first time, we explicitly represent the sources of riverine DOC with seasonal discharge based on climatological field estimates. Through a suite of numerical experiments, we explore the distribution of DOC-like tracers with realistic riverine sources and a simple linear decay to represent remineralization through microbial degradation. The model reproduces the slope of the DOC-salinity relationship observed in the eastern and western Arctic basins when the DOC tracer lifetime is about 10 years, consistent with published inferences from field data. The new empirical parameterization of riverine DOC and the regional circulation and biogeochemical model provide new tools for application in both regional and global change studies.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Manizza, Manfredi</author><author>Follows, Michael J.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Key, Robert M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Changes in the Arctic Ocean CO$_2$ sink (1996--2007): A regional model analysis</title><secondary-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</full-title></periodical><pages>1108-1118</pages><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords><keyword>Arctic Ocean</keyword><keyword>ocean productivity</keyword><keyword>sea ice</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><isbn>0886-6236</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2012GB004491</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Manizza et al. - 2013 - Changes in the Arctic Ocean CO$_2$ sink (1996--2007) A regional model analysis.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2012GB004491</url><url>http://doi.wiley.com/10.1002/2012GB004491</url></web-urls></urls><label>CMS</label><abstract>The rapid recent decline of Arctic Ocean sea ice area increases the flux of solar radiation available for primary production and the area of open water for air-sea gas exchange. We use a regional physical-biogeochemical model of the Arctic Ocean, forced by the National Centers for Environmental Prediction/National Center for Atmospheric Research atmospheric reanalysis, to evaluate the mean present-day CO2 sink and its temporal evolution. During the 1996–2007 period, the model suggests that the Arctic average sea surface temperature warmed by 0.04°C a−1, that sea ice area decreased by ∼0.1 × 106 km2 a−1, and that the biological drawdown of dissolved inorganic carbon increased. The simulated 1996–2007 time-mean Arctic Ocean CO2 sink is 58 ± 6 Tg C a−1. The increase in ice-free ocean area and consequent carbon drawdown during this period enhances the CO2 sink by ∼1.4 Tg C a−1, consistent with estimates based on extrapolations of sparse data. A regional analysis suggests that during the 1996–2007 period, the shelf regions of the Laptev, East Siberian, Chukchi, and Beaufort Seas experienced an increase in the efficiency of their biological pump due to decreased sea ice area, especially during the 2004–2007 period, consistent with independently published estimates of primary production. In contrast, the CO2 sink in the Barents Sea is reduced during the 2004–2007 period due to a dominant control by warming and decreasing solubility. Thus, the effect of decreasing sea ice area and increasing sea surface temperature partially cancel, though the former is dominant.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Book Section">7</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fox-Kemper, Baylor</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors><secondary-authors><author>Hecht, Matthew</author><author>Hasumi, Hiroyasu</author></secondary-authors></contributors><titles><title>Can Large Eddy Simulation Techniques Improve Mesoscale Rich Ocean Models?</title><secondary-title>Ocean Modeling in an Eddying Regime</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Ocean Modeling in an Eddying Regime</full-title></periodical><pages>319-337</pages><keywords><keyword>Ocean circulation—Mathematical models</keyword><keyword>Oceanography—Mathematical models</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2008</year></dates><pub-location>Washington, D.C.</pub-location><publisher>AGU</publisher><isbn>9781118666432</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/177GM19</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fox-Kemper, Menemenlis - 2008 - Can Large Eddy Simulation Techniques Improve Mesoscale Rich Ocean Models.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/177GM19</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>This chapter contains sections titled: * Introduction * Nonlinear Viscosities and diffusivities * Filtering and Dynamical Adjustment * Summary and Discussion</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Brix, Holger</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Jahn, Oliver</author><author>Wang, D.</author><author>Bowman, Kevin W.</author><author>Zhang, H.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Using Green's Functions to initialize and adjust a global, eddying ocean biogeochemistry general circulation model</title><secondary-title>Ocean Modelling</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Ocean Modelling</full-title></periodical><pages>1-14</pages><volume>95</volume><keywords><keyword>Carbon monitoring system</keyword><keyword>Data assimilation</keyword><keyword>Green's function</keyword><keyword>Ocean biogeochemical circulation model</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.ocemod.2015.07.008</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Brix et al. - 2015 - Using Green's Functions to initialize and adjust a global, eddying ocean biogeochemistry general circulation model.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><label>CMS</label><abstract>The NASA Carbon Monitoring System (CMS) Flux Project aims to attribute changes in the atmospheric accumulation of carbon dioxide to spatially resolved fluxes by utilizing the full suite of NASA data, models, and assimilation capabilities. For the oceanic part of this project, we introduce ECCO2-Darwin, a new ocean biogeochemistry general circulation model based on combining the following pre-existing components: (i) a full-depth, eddying, global-ocean configuration of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm), (ii) an adjoint-method-based estimate of ocean circulation from the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean, Phase II (ECCO2) project, (iii) the MIT ecosystem model &quot;Darwin&quot;, and (iv) a marine carbon chemistry model. Air-sea gas exchange coefficients and initial conditions of dissolved inorganic carbon, alkalinity, and oxygen are adjusted using a Green's Functions approach in order to optimize modeled air-sea CO&lt;inf&gt;2&lt;/inf&gt; fluxes. Data constraints include observations of carbon dioxide partial pressure (pCO&lt;inf&gt;2&lt;/inf&gt;) for 2009-2010, global air-sea CO&lt;inf&gt;2&lt;/inf&gt; flux estimates, and the seasonal cycle of the Takahashi et al. (2009) Atlas. The model sensitivity experiments (or Green's Functions) include simulations that start from different initial conditions as well as experiments that perturb air-sea gas exchange parameters and the ratio of particulate inorganic to organic carbon. The Green's Functions approach yields a linear combination of these sensitivity experiments that minimizes model-data differences. The resulting initial conditions and gas exchange coefficients are then used to integrate the ECCO2-Darwin model forward. Despite the small number (six) of control parameters, the adjusted simulation is significantly closer to the data constraints (37% cost function reduction, i.e., reduction in the model-data difference, relative to the baseline simulation) and to independent observations (e.g., alkalinity). The adjusted air-sea gas exchange parameter differs by only 3% from the baseline value and has little impact (-0.1%) on the cost function. The particulate inorganic to organic carbon ratio was increased more than threefold and reduced the cost function by 22% relative to the baseline integration, indicating a significant influence of biology on air-sea gas exchange. The largest contribution to cost reduction (35%) comes from the adjustment of initial conditions. In addition to reducing biases relative to observations, the adjusted simulation exhibits smaller model drift than the baseline. We estimate drift by integrating the model with repeated 2009 atmospheric forcing for seven years and find a volume-weighted drift reduction of, for example, 12.5% for nitrate and 30% for oxygen in the top 300 m. Although there remain several regions with large model-data discrepancies, for example, overly strong carbon uptake in the Southern Ocean, the adjusted simulation is a first step towards a more accurate representation of the ocean carbon cycle at high spatial and temporal resolution.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Xu, Yun</author><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Koppes, Michele</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Numerical experiments on subaqueous melting of {Greenland} tidewater glaciers in response to ocean warming and enhanced subglacial discharge</title><secondary-title>Annals of Glaciology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Annals of Glaciology</full-title></periodical><pages>229-234</pages><volume>53</volume><issue>60</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2012</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.3189/2012AoG60A139</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Xu et al. - 2012 - Numerical experiments on subaqueous melting of {Greenland} tidewater glaciers in response to ocean warming and enhanc.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The largest dischargers of ice in Greenland are glaciers that terminate in the ocean and melt in contact with sea water. Studies of ice-sheet/ocean interactions have mostly focused on melting beneath near-horizontal floating ice shelves. For tidewater glaciers, melting instead takes place along the vertical face of the calving front. Here we modify the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm) to include ice melting from a calving face with the freshwater outflow at the glacier grounding line. We use the model to predict melt rates and their sensitivity to ocean thermal forcing and to subglacial discharge. We find that melt rates increase with approximately the one-third power of the subglacial water flux, and increase linearly with ocean thermal forcing. Our simulations indicate that, consistent with limited field data, melting ceases when subglacial discharge is shut off, and reaches several meters per day when subglacial discharge is high in the summer. These results are a first step toward a more realistic representation of subglacial discharge and of ocean thermal forcing on the subaqueous melting of tidewater glaciers in a numerical ocean model. Our results illustrate that the ice-front melting process is both complex and strongly time-dependent.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Lee, Tong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Using Green's Functions to calibrate an ocean general circulation model</title><secondary-title>Monthly Weather Review</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Monthly Weather Review</full-title></periodical><pages>1224-1240</pages><volume>133</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords><keyword>monthly weather review</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2005</year></dates><isbn>0027-0644</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/MWR2912.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Fukumori, Lee - 2005 - Using Green's Functions to calibrate an ocean general circulation model.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Green’s functions provide a simple yet effective method to test and to calibrate general circulation model (GCM) parameterizations, to study and to quantify model and data errors, to correct model biases and trends, and to blend estimates from different solutions and data products. The method is applied to an ocean GCM, resulting in substantial improvements of the solution relative to observations when compared to prior estimates: overall model bias and drift are reduced and there is a 10%–30% increase in explained variance. Within the context of this optimization, the following new estimates for commonly used ocean GCM parameters are obtained. Background vertical diffusivity is (15.1 0.1) 10-6 m2 s2. Background vertical viscosity is (18 3) 10-6 m2 s2. The critical bulk Richardson number, which sets boundary layer depth, is Ric = 0.354 0.004. The threshold gradient Richardson number for shear instability vertical mixing is Ri0 = 0.699 0.008. The estimated isopycnal diffusivity coefficient ranges from 550 to 1350 m2 s2, with the largest values occurring at depth in regions of increased mesoscale eddy activity. Surprisingly, the estimated isopycnal diffusivity exhibits a 5%–35% decrease near the surface. Improved estimates of initial and boundary conditions are also obtained. The above estimates are the backbone of a quasi-operational, global-ocean circulation analysis system.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Chechelnitsky, Michael</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Error Estimates for an Ocean General Circulation Model from Altimeter and Acoustic Tomography Data</title><secondary-title>Monthly Weather Review</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Monthly Weather Review</full-title></periodical><pages>763-778</pages><volume>128</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2000</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/1520-0493(2000)128&lt;0763:EEFAOG&gt;2.0.CO;2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Chechelnitsky - 2000 - Error Estimates for an Ocean General Circulation Model from Altimeter and Acoustic Tomography Data.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/abs/10.1175/1520-0493%282000%29128%3C0763%3AEEFAOG%3E2.0.CO%3B2</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>An offline approach is proposed for the estimation of model and data error covariance matrices whereby covariance matrices of model data residuals are &quot;matched&quot; to their theoretical expectations using familiar least-squares methods. This covariance matching approach is both a powerful diagnostic tool for addressing theoretical questions and an efficient estimator for real data assimilation studies. Provided that model and data errors are independent, that error propagation is approximately linear, and that an observability condition is met, it is in theory possible to fully resolve covariance matrices for both model and data errors. In practice, however, due to large uncertainties in sample estimates of covariance matrices, the number of statistically significant parameters that can be estimated is two to three orders of magnitude smaller than the total number of independent observations. The covariance matching approach is applied in the North Pacific (5°-60° N, 132°-252° E) to TOPEX/Poseidon sea level anomaly data, acoustic tomography data from the Acoustic Thermometry of Ocean Climate Project, and a GCM. A reduced state linear model that describes large-scale internal (baroclinic) error dynamics is constructed. Twin experiments suggest that altimetric data are ill suited to estimating the statistics of the vertical GCM error structure, but that such estimates can in theory be obtained using acoustic data. The particular GCM integration exhibits a warming trend relative to TOPEX/Poseidon data of order 1 cm yr-1 corresponding to a peak warming of up to 0.2°C yr-1 in the acoustic data at depths ranging from 50 to 200 m. At the annual cycle, GCM and TOPEX/Poseidon sea level anomaly are in phase, but GCM amplitude is 2 cm smaller, with the error confined above 200-m depth. After removal of trends and annual cycles, the low-frequency/wavenumber (periods &gt;2 months, wavelengths &gt;16°) TOPEX/Poseidon sea level anomaly is order 6 cm2. The GCM explains about 40% of that variance. By covariance matching, it is estimated that 60% of the GCM-TOPEX/Poseidon residual variance is consistent with the reduced state linear model.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Halkides, Daria J.</author><author>Waliser, Duane E.</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Guan, Bin</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Quantifying the processes controlling intraseasonal mixed-layer temperature variability in the tropical Indian Ocean</title></titles><periodical/><volume>120</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Indian Ocean</keyword><keyword>Intraseasonal</keyword><keyword>M</keyword><keyword>Mixed-layer</keyword><keyword>[ECCO</keyword><keyword>intraseasonal</keyword><keyword>mixed-layer</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2014JC010139</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Halkides et al. - 2015 - Quantifying the processes controlling intraseasonal mixed-layer temperature variability in the tropical Indian.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Preliminary estimates of North Pacific circulation from combined altimetry, acoustic tomography, and a general circulation model</title><secondary-title>International WOCE Newsletter</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>International WOCE Newsletter</full-title></periodical><pages>7-10</pages><issue>25</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1997</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis et al. - 1997 - Preliminary estimates of North Pacific circulation from combined altimetry, acoustic tomography, and a genera.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Cheng, Benny</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Köhl, Armin</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Adcroft, Alistair J.</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Zhang, Jinlun</author><author>Henze, Christopher E.</author><author>Taft, J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The ECCO high-resolution global-ocean state estimation initiative</title><secondary-title>EOS Transactions AGU</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>EOS Transactions AGU</full-title></periodical><pages>OS21H-02</pages><volume>84</volume><issue>52</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2003</year></dates><notes>Available at http://ecco.jpl.nasa.gov/cube_sphere/</notes><research-notes>Available at http://ecco.jpl.nasa.gov/cube_sphere/</research-notes><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Generic">31</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Kraeutner, Paul</author><author>Balla, P C</author><author>WeymondYee</author><author>Johnson, Ernesto</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>ASTRID User Manual</title></titles><periodical/><keywords/><dates><year>1989</year></dates><pub-location>Marine Technology Centre, 9865 West Saanich Road, Sidney, B.C., V8L 3S1</pub-location><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">3</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Farmer, David M.</author></authors><secondary-authors><author>Bhargava, Vijay K</author></secondary-authors></contributors><titles><title>An Acoustic Instrument for Studying the Turbulent Oceanic Boundary Layer in the {Arctic}</title><secondary-title>Canadian Conference on Electrical and Computer Engineering</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Canadian Conference on Electrical and Computer Engineering</full-title></periodical><pages>48-51</pages><keywords/><dates><year>1988</year></dates><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Stammer, Detlef</author><author>Davis, R.</author><author>Fu, Lee-Lueng</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Giering, Ralf</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Marotzke, Jochem</author><author>Marshall, John C.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Niiler, Pearn Peter</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Zlotnicki, Victor</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The Consortium for Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO)</title><secondary-title>Report</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Report</full-title></periodical><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><pub-location>9500 Gilman Dr., La Jolla, CA 92093-0239; also available at http://www.ecco.ucsd.edu/report/report_1/report_1.html</pub-location><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">3</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Henze, Christopher E.</author><author>Nelson, B</author><author>Ciotti, Robert B.</author><author>Chaudhuri, A</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Global {llcXXXX} simulations with tides</title><secondary-title>Presentation at annual {ECCO} meeting</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Presentation at annual {ECCO} meeting</full-title></periodical><keywords/><dates><year>2014</year></dates><notes>available at
\href{http://ecco2.org/meetings/2014/Jan_MIT/presentations/ThursdayPM/05_menemenlis.pdf}
{http://ecco2.org/meetings/2014/Jan_MIT/presentations/ThursdayPM/05_menemenlis.pdf}</notes><research-notes>available at
\href{http://ecco2.org/meetings/2014/Jan_MIT/presentations/ThursdayPM/05_menemenlis.pdf}
{http://ecco2.org/meetings/2014/Jan_MIT/presentations/ThursdayPM/05_menemenlis.pdf}</research-notes><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Report">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Köhl, Armin</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Stammer, Detlef</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The Impact of ECCO Surface Forcing Fields on the Results of a Global 1/4-deg Model</title></titles><periodical/><issue>30</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2005</year></dates><pub-location>9500 Gilman Dr., La Jolla, CA 92093-0239</pub-location><notes>available at http://www.ecco-group.org/reports.html</notes><research-notes>available at http://www.ecco-group.org/reports.html</research-notes><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Generic">31</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Adcroft, Alistair J.</author><author>Campin, Jean-Michel</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Evangelinos, Constantinos</author><author>Ferreira, David</author><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Fox-Kemper, Baylor</author><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Hill, Ed</author><author>Hill, Helen</author><author>Jahn, Oliver</author><author>Losch, Martin</author><author>Marshall, John C.</author><author>Maze, Guillaume</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Molod, Andrea</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>MITgcm user manual</title></titles><periodical/><keywords/><dates><year>2015</year></dates><notes>available at http://mitgcm.org/public/r2_manual/latest/online_documents/manual.pdf</notes><research-notes>available at http://mitgcm.org/public/r2_manual/latest/online_documents/manual.pdf</research-notes><urls/></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Thesis">2</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Acoustical measurement of velocity , vorticity and turbulence in the Arctic boundary layer beneath ice</title></titles><periodical/><keywords/><dates><year>1993</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis - 1993 - Acoustical measurement of velocity , vorticity and turbulence in the Arctic boundary layer beneath ice.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Howe, Bruce M.</author><author>Mercer, James A.</author><author>Spindel, Robert C.</author><author>Baggeroer, Arthur B.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author><author>Birdsall, Theodore G.</author><author>Metzger, K.</author><author>Clark, C.</author><author>Colosi, J. A.</author><author>Curnuelle, B. D.</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Munk, Walter H.</author><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Costa, D.</author><author>Forbes, Andrew M. G.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Multimegameter-range acoustic data obtained by bottom-mounted hydrophone arrays for measurement of ocean temperature</title><secondary-title>IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering</full-title></periodical><pages>202-214</pages><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><isbn>0364-9059 VO - 24</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/48.757271</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dushaw et al. - 1999 - Multimegameter-range acoustic data obtained by bottom-mounted hydrophone arrays for measurement of ocean temperat.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Acoustic signals transmitted from the ATOC source on Pioneer Seamount off the coast of California have been received at various sites around the Pacific Basin since January 1996. We describe data obtained using bottom-mounted receivers, including U.S. Navy Sound Surveilance System arrays, at ranges up to 5 Mm from the Pioneer Seamount source. Stable identifiable ray arrivals are observed in several cases, but some receiving arrays are not well suited to detecting the direct ray arrivals. At 5-Mm range, travel-time variations at tidal frequencies (about 50 ms peak to peak) agree well with predicted values, providing verification of the acoustic measurements as well as the tidal model. On the longest and northernmost acoustic paths, the time series of resolved ray travel times show an annual cycle peak-to-peak variation of about 1 s and other fluctuations caused by natural oceanic variability. An annual cycle is not evident in travel times from shorter acoustic paths in the eastern Pacific, though only one realization of the annual cycle is available. The low-pass-filtered travel times are estimated to an accuracy of about 10 ms. This travel-time uncertainty corresponds to errors in range- and depth-averaged temperature of only a few millidegrees, while the annual peak-to-peak variation in temperature averaged horizontally over the acoustic path and vertically over the upper 1 km of ocean is up to 0.5°C.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Colosi, J. A.</author><author>Baggeroer, Arthur B.</author><author>Birdsall, Theodore G.</author><author>Clark, C.</author><author>Cornuelle, Bruce D.</author><author>Costa, D.</author><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Forbes, Andrew M. G.</author><author>Howe, Bruce M.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mercer, James A.</author><author>Metzger, K.</author><author>Munk, Walter H.</author><author>Spindel, Robert C.</author><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A review of recent results on ocean acoustic wave propagation in random media: basin scales</title><secondary-title>IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engineering</full-title></periodical><pages>138-155</pages><volume>24</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/48.757267</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Colosi et al. - 1999 - A review of recent results on ocean acoustic wave propagation in random media basin scales.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/lpdocs/epic03/wrapper.htm?arnumber=757267</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>In November 1994, the Acoustic Thermometry of Ocean Climate (ATOC) initiated the Acoustic Engineering Test (AET). Acoustic fluctuations of low-frequency pulse propagation at ranges of 1000 to 5000 km were observed. Analysis of the data revealed new and unexpected results for the physics of ocean acoustic wave propagation in random media.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Liu, Junjie</author><author>Bowman, Kevin W.</author><author>Lee, Meemong</author><author>Henze, Daven K.</author><author>Bousserez, Nicolas</author><author>Brix, Holger</author><author>Collatz, George James</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Ott, Lesley E.</author><author>Pawson, Steven</author><author>Jones, Dylan</author><author>Nassar, Ray</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Carbon monitoring system flux estimation and attribution: Impact of ACOS-GOSAT XCO$_2$ sampling on the inference of terrestrial biospheric sources and sinks</title><secondary-title>Tellus, Series B: Chemical and Physical Meteorology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Tellus, Series B: Chemical and Physical Meteorology</full-title></periodical><volume>66</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords><keyword>Biased sampling</keyword><keyword>GOSAT</keyword><keyword>Monte carlo</keyword><keyword>NASA CMS-flux</keyword><keyword>OCO-2</keyword><keyword>Variational inversion</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2014</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.3402/tellusb.v66.22486</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Liu et al. - 2014 - Carbon monitoring system flux estimation and attribution Impact of ACOS-GOSAT XCO$_2$ sampling on the inference of t.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><label>CMS</label><abstract>Using an Observing System Simulation Experiment (OSSE), we investigate the impact of JAXA Greenhouse gases Observing SATellite ‘IBUKI’ (GOSAT) sampling on the estimation of terrestrial biospheric flux with the NASA Carbon Monitoring System Flux (CMS-Flux) estimation and attribution strategy. The simulated observations in the OSSE use the actual column carbon dioxide (X CO 2 ) b2.9 retrieval sensitivity and quality control for the year 2010 processed through the Atmospheric CO 2 Observations from Space algorithm. CMS-Flux is a variational inversion system that uses the GEOS-Chem forward and adjoint model forced by a suite of observationally constrained fluxes from ocean, land and anthropogenic models. We investigate the impact of GOSAT sampling on flux estimation in two aspects: 1) random error uncertainty reduction and 2) the global and regional bias in posterior flux resulted from the spatiotemporally biased GOSAT sampling. Based on Monte Carlo calculations, we find that global average flux uncertainty reduction ranges from 25% in September to 60% in July. When aggregated to the 11 land regions designated by the phase 3 of the Atmospheric Tracer Transport Model Intercomparison Project, the annual mean uncertainty reduction ranges from 10% over North American boreal to 38% over South American temperate, which is driven by observational coverage and the magnitude of prior flux uncertainty. The uncertainty reduction over the South American tropical region is 30%, even with sparse observation coverage. We show that this reduction results from the large prior flux uncertainty and the impact of non-local observations. Given the assumed prior error statistics, the degree of freedom for signal is ~1132 for 1-yr of the 74 055 GOSAT X CO 2 observations, which indicates that GOSAT provides ~1132 independent pieces of information about surface fluxes. We quantify the impact of GOSAT’s spatiotemporally sampling on the posterior flux, and find that a 0.7 gigatons of carbon bias in the global annual posterior flux resulted from the seasonally and diurnally biased sampling when using a diagonal prior flux error covariance. Keywords: NASA CMS-Flux, GOSAT, OCO-2, variational inversion, biased sampling, Monte Carlo (Published: 9 May 2014) Citation: Tellus B 2014, 66 , 22486, http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/tellusb.v66.22486</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gruber, Nicolas</author><author>Gloor, Manuel</author><author>Mikaloff Fletcher, Sara E.</author><author>Doney, Scott C.</author><author>Dutkiewicz, Stephanie</author><author>Follows, Michael J.</author><author>Gerber, Markus</author><author>Jacobson, Andrew R.</author><author>Joos, Fortunat</author><author>Lindsay, Keith</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mouchet, Anne</author><author>Müller, Simon A.</author><author>Sarmiento, Jorge L.</author><author>Takahashi, Taro</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Oceanic sources, sinks, and transport of atmospheric CO$_2$</title><secondary-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Global Biogeochemical Cycles</full-title></periodical><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><isbn>0886-6236</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2008GB003349</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gruber et al. - 2009 - Oceanic sources, sinks, and transport of atmospheric CO$_2$.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We synthesize estimates of the contemporary net air-sea CO2 flux on the basis of an inversion of interior ocean carbon observations using a suite of 10 ocean general circulation models (Mikaloff Fletcher et al., 2006, 2007) and compare them to estimates based on a new climatology of the air-sea difference of the partial pressure of CO2 (pCO2) (Takahashi et al., 2008). These two independent flux estimates reveal a consistent description of the regional distribution of annual mean sources and sinks of atmospheric CO2 for the decade of the 1990s and the early 2000s with differences at the regional level of generally less than 0.1 Pg C a?1. This distribution is characterized by outgassing in the tropics, uptake in midlatitudes, and comparatively small fluxes in the high latitudes. Both estimates point toward a small (??0.3 Pg C a?1) contemporary CO2 sink in the Southern Ocean (south of 44?S), a result of the near cancellation between a substantial outgassing of natural CO2 and a strong uptake of anthropogenic CO2.A notable exception in the generally good agreement between the two estimates exists within the Southern Ocean: the ocean inversion suggests a relatively uniform uptake, while the pCO2-based estimate suggests strong uptake in the region between 58?S and 44?S, and a source in the region south of 58?S. Globally and for a nominal period between 1995 and 2000, the contemporary net air-sea flux of CO2 is estimated to be?1.7 ± 0.4 Pg C a?1 (inversion) and ?1.4 ± 0.7 Pg C a?1 (pCO2-climatology), respectively, consisting of an outgassing flux of river-derived carbon of ?+0.5 Pg C a?1, and an uptake flux of anthropogenic carbon of ?2.2 ± 0.3 Pg C a?1 (inversion) and ?1.9 ± 0.7 Pg C a?1 (pCO2-climatology). The two flux estimates also imply a consistent description of the contemporary meridional transport of carbon with southward ocean transport throughout most of the Atlantic basin, and strong equatorward convergence in the Indo-Pacific basins. Both transport estimates suggest a small hemispheric asymmetry with a southward transport of between?0.2 and?0.3 Pg C a?1 across the equator. While the convergence of these two independent estimates is encouraging and suggests that it is now possible to provide relatively tight constraints for the net air-sea CO2 fluxes at the regional basis, both studies are limited by their lack of consideration of long-term changes in the ocean carbon cycle, such as the recent possible stalling in the expected growth of the Southern Ocean carbon sink.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author><author>Xu, Yun</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Mouginot, Jeremie</author><author>Scheuchl, B.</author><author>Li, X.</author><author>Morlighem, M.</author><author>Seroussi, H.</author><author>van den Broeke, Michiel R.</author><author>Fenty, Ian G.</author><author>Cai, Cilan</author><author>An, L.</author><author>de Fleurian, B.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Modeling of ocean-induced ice melt rates of five west Greenland glaciers over the past two decades</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>6374-6382</pages><volume>43</volume><issue>12</issue><keywords><keyword>calving</keyword><keyword>glaciology</keyword><keyword>greenland</keyword><keyword>ice-ocean interaction</keyword><keyword>mass balance</keyword><keyword>subaqueous melt</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2016GL068784</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Rignot et al. - 2016 - Modeling of ocean-induced ice melt rates of five west Greenland glaciers over the past two decades.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>High-resolution, three-dimensional simulations from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model ocean model are used to calculate the subaqueous melt rate of the calving faces of Umiamako, Rinks, Kangerdlugssup, Store, and Kangilerngata glaciers, west Greenland, from 1992 to 2015. Model forcing is from monthly reconstructions of ocean state and ice sheet runoff. Results are analyzed in combination with observations of bathymetry, bed elevation, ice front retreat, and glacier speed. We calculate that subaqueous melt rates are 2–3 times larger in summer compared to winter and doubled in magnitude since the 1990s due to enhanced subglacial runoff and 1.6 ± 0.3°C warmer ocean temperature. Umiamako and Kangilerngata retreated rapidly in the 2000s when subaqueous melt rates exceeded the calving rates and ice front retreated to deeper bed elevation. In contrast, Store, Kangerdlugssup, and Rinks have remained stable because their subaqueous melt rates are 3–4 times lower than their calving rates, i.e., the glaciers are dominated by calving processes.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ott, Lesley E.</author><author>Pawson, Steven</author><author>Collatz, George James</author><author>Gregg, Watson W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Brix, Holger</author><author>Rousseaux, Cecile S.</author><author>Bowman, Kevin W.</author><author>Liu, Junjie</author><author>Eldering, Annmarie</author><author>Gunson, Michael R.</author><author>Kawa, Stephan Randolph</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Assessing the magnitude of CO$_2$ flux uncertainty in atmospheric CO$_2$ records using products from NASA's Carbon Monitoring Flux Pilot Project</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research Atmospheres</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research Atmospheres</full-title></periodical><pages>734-765</pages><volume>120</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>CMS</keyword><keyword>CO2</keyword><keyword>GOSAT</keyword><keyword>biosphere</keyword><keyword>modeling</keyword><keyword>ocean</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2014JD022411</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Ott et al. - 2015 - Assessing the magnitude of CO$_2$ flux uncertainty in atmospheric CO$_2$ records using products from NASA's Carbon M.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><label>CMS</label><abstract>NASA's Carbon Monitoring System Flux Pilot Project (FPP) was designed to better understand contemporary carbon fluxes by bringing together state-of-the art models with remote sensing data sets. Here we report on simulations using NASA's Goddard Earth Observing System Model, version 5 (GEOS-5) which was used to evaluate the consistency of two different sets of observationally informed land and ocean fluxes with atmospheric CO2 records. Despite the observation inputs, the average difference in annual terrestrial biosphere flux between the two land (NASA Ames Carnegie-Ames-Stanford-Approach (CASA) and CASA-Global Fire Emissions Database version 3 (GFED)) models is 1.7 Pg C for 2009–2010. Ocean models (NASA's Ocean Biogeochemical Model (NOBM) and Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean Phase II (ECCO2)-Darwin) differ by 35% in their global estimates of carbon flux with particularly strong disagreement in high latitudes. Based upon combinations of terrestrial and ocean fluxes, GEOS-5 reasonably simulated the seasonal cycle observed at Northern Hemisphere surface sites and by the Greenhouse gases Observing SATellite (GOSAT) while the model struggled to simulate the seasonal cycle at Southern Hemisphere surface locations. Though GEOS-5 was able to reasonably reproduce the patterns of XCO2 observed by GOSAT, it struggled to reproduce these aspects of Atmospheric Infrared Sounder observations. Despite large differences between land and ocean flux estimates, resulting differences in atmospheric mixing ratio were small, typically less than 5 ppm at the surface and 3 ppm in the XCO2 column. A statistical analysis based on the variability of observations shows that flux differences of these magnitudes are difficult to distinguish from inherent measurement variability, regardless of the measurement platform.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Book Section">7</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Ponte, Rui M.</author><author>Evangelinos, C</author><author>Forget, Gaël</author><author>Mazloff, Matthew R.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Vinogradov, S</author><author>Wunsch, Carl I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Combining Altimetric and All Other Data with a General Circulation Model.</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of the 15 Years of Progress in Radar Altimetry Symposium</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the 15 Years of Progress in Radar Altimetry Symposium</full-title></periodical><volume>SP-614</volume><issue>614</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2006</year></dates><isbn>9290929251 | 9789290929253</isbn><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Heimbach et al. - 2006 - Combining Altimetric and All Other Data with a General Circulation Model.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The TOPEX/POSEIDON mission was formulated in conjunction with the World Ocean Circulation Experiment (WOCE). Although altimetric data are by far the largest ocean data set that emerged from that experiment, it was recognized from the outset that the best estimate of the ocean circulation and its variability would be made by combining all the data with a good general circulation model. The US ECCO-GODAE consortium has now produced useful estimates of the three-dimensional time evolving ocean circulation at 1 degree lateral resolution, 23 layers in the vertical, over the time period 1992-2004. At the present time, the solution represents a least-squares misfit to about 410 million separate observational constraints. A large variety of fields can be analyzed in the results, but the focus here will be on the overturning circulation and its changes over this time period. The residual model/data misfits raise difficult questions about remaining errors in the altimetric/geoid fields.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Munk, Walter H.</author><author>Spindel, Robert C.</author><author>Mercer, James A.</author><author>Howe, Bruce M.</author><author>Metzger, K.</author><author>Birdsall, Theodore G.</author><author>Andrew, R. K.</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Cornuelle, Bruce D.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A decade of acoustic thermometry in the North Pacific Ocean</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><volume>114</volume><issue>7</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><isbn>0148-0227</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2008JC005124</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dushaw et al. - 2009 - A decade of acoustic thermometry in the North Pacific Ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Over the decade 1996–2006, acoustic sources located off central California (1996–1999) and north of Kauai (1997–1999, 2002–2006) transmitted to receivers distributed throughout the northeast and north central Pacific. The acoustic travel times are inherently spatially integrating, which suppresses mesoscale variability and provides a precise measure of ray-averaged temperature. Daily average travel times at 4-day intervals provide excellent temporal resolution of the large-scale thermal field. The interannual, seasonal, and shorter-period variability is large, with substantial changes sometimes occurring in only a few weeks. Linear trends estimated over the decade are small compared to the interannual variability and inconsistent from path to path, with some acoustic paths warming slightly and others cooling slightly. The measured travel times are compared with travel times derived from four independent estimates of the North Pacific: (1) climatology, as represented by the World Ocean Atlas 2005 (WOA05); (2) objective analysis of the upper-ocean temperature field derived from satellite altimetry and in situ profiles; (3) an analysis provided by the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean project, as implemented at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL-ECCO); and (4) simulation results from a high-resolution configuration of the Parallel Ocean Program (POP) model. The acoustic data show that WOA05 is a better estimate of the time mean hydrography than either the JPL-ECCO or the POP estimates, both of which proved incapable of reproducing the observed acoustic arrival patterns. The comparisons of time series provide a stringent test of the large-scale temperature variability in the models. The differences are sometimes substantial, indicating that acoustic thermometry data can provide significant additional constraints for numerical ocean models.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Flexas, M. Mar</author><author>Schodlok, Michael P.</author><author>Padman, Laurie</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Orsi, A. H.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Role of tides on the formation of the Antarctic Slope Front at the Weddell-Scotia Confluence</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research C: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research C: Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>3658-3680</pages><volume>120</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords><keyword>Antarctic Slope Current</keyword><keyword>Antarctic Slope Front</keyword><keyword>SASSI</keyword><keyword>Scotia sea</keyword><keyword>numerical model</keyword><keyword>tides</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2014JC010372</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Flexas et al. - 2015 - Role of tides on the formation of the Antarctic Slope Front at the Weddell-Scotia Confluence.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The structure of the Antarctic Slope Front (ASF) and the associated Antarctic Slope Current (ASC) on the Scotia Sea side of the Weddell-Scotia Confluence (WSC) is described using data from a hydrographic survey and three 1 year long moorings across the continental slope. The ASC in this region flows westward along isobaths with an annual mean speed of approximate to 0.2 m s(-1), with time variability dominated by the K-1 and O-1 tidal diurnal constituents, a narrowband oscillation with approximate to 2-week period attributable to the spring/neap tidal cycle, and seasonal variability. Realistic and idealized high-resolution numerical simulations are used to determine the contribution of tides to the structure of the ASF and the speed of the ASC. Two simulations forced by realistic atmospheric forcing and boundary conditions integrated with and without tidal forcing show that tidal forcing is essential to reproduce the measured ASF/ASC cross-slope structure, the time variability at our moorings, and the reduced stratification within the WSC. Two idealized simulations run with tide-only forcing, one with a homogeneous ocean and the other with initial vertical stratification that is laterally homogeneous, show that tides can generate the ASC and ASF through volume flux convergence along the slope initiated by effects including the Lagrangian component of tidal rectification and mixing at the seabed and in the stratified ocean interior. Climate models that exclude the effects of tides will not correctly represent the ASF and ASC or their influence on the injection of intermediate and dense waters from the WSC to the deep ocean.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Xing, Z F</author><author>Fu, Lee-Lueng</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Effects of the Indonesian Throughflow on the Pacific and Indian oceans</title><secondary-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>1404-1429</pages><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords><keyword>appearance reality</keyword><keyword>climatology</keyword><keyword>el-nino</keyword><keyword>exchange</keyword><keyword>general-circulation model</keyword><keyword>north pacific</keyword><keyword>originate</keyword><keyword>parameterization</keyword><keyword>thermocline</keyword><keyword>water</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2002</year></dates><isbn>0022-3670</isbn><electronic-resource-num>Doi 10.1175/1520-0485(2002)032&lt;1404:Eotito&gt;2.0.Co;2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Lee et al. - 2002 - Effects of the Indonesian Throughflow on the Pacific and Indian oceans.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Effects of the Indonesian Throughflow (ITF) on the circulation and thermal structure of the Pacific and Indian Oceans are studied by comparing solutions of a near-global ocean general circulation model with open and closed Indonesian passages from 1981 to 1997. The ITF contributes to the maintenance of the model circulation system around eastern Australia and the southern Indian Ocean. Blockage of the ITF weakens the Indian Ocean South Equatorial Current and Agulhas Current and strengthens the East Australian Current. The ITF does not affect the Mindanao Current, but drains waters carried by this current into the Indian Ocean and thus reduces tropical-subtropical exchange in the North Pacific. Meanwhile, it helps maintain a stronger New Guinea Coastal Undercurrent and thus enhances tropical-subtropical exchange in the south. Water parcels traveling along the western boundary of the South Pacific cross the equator in the presence of the ITF but are confined to the Southern Hemisphere without the ITF. The southern &quot;exchange window'' in which subducted waters can reach the Tropics is wider with than without the ITF. Some parcels from the southern subtropics can reach the Tropics with open ITF, but recirculate back to the subtropical gyre when the ITF is closed. These &quot;excess'' recirculated parcels reach several degrees farther south and outcrop north of Tasmania. The consequence on sea surface temperature (SST) there may have an important implication to the local climate. Blockage of the ITF depresses the mean thermocline of the tropical Pacific, increases SST in the central to eastern equatorial Pacific, and thus reduces the SST difference between the warm pool and cold tongue. It also raises the mean thermocline of the Indian Ocean (especially the southern Indian Ocean) and decreases SST in the southern Indian Ocean. Blockage of the ITF reduces seasonal-to-interannual thermocline fluctuations in the central to eastern equatorial Pacific because the resulting deeper thermocline attenuates fluctuations in response to local Ekman pumping. The opposite is true in the southern Indian Ocean for the interannual timescale. However, seasonal thermocline fluctuation in that area is weakened when the ITF is blocked (despite a shallower thermocline). It indicates that local Ekman pumping is not the dominant mechanism controlling seasonal thermocline variability there as previously suggested. Radiation of planetary waves from the ITF area and advection by the ITF-dependent South Equatorial Current could also be important. Blockage of the ITF also reduces interannual variability of SST in the eastern equatorial Pacific and enhances those in the tropical southern Indian Ocean and south of Tasmania. The results indicate that the ITF may affect El Nino-Southern Oscillation by modifying tropical-subtropical exchanges, mean tropical thermocline structure, mean SST difference between the warm pool and cold tongue, and seasonal-to-interannual variabilities of thermocline depth and SST.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ngeve, Magdalene N.</author><author>Van der Stocken, Tom</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Koedam, Nico</author><author>Triest, Ludwig</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Contrasting effects of historical sea level rise and contemporary ocean currents on regional gene flow of rhizophora racemosa in eastern atlantic mangroves</title><secondary-title>PLoS ONE</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>PLoS ONE</full-title></periodical><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2016</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1371/journal.pone.0150950</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Ngeve et al. - 2016 - Contrasting effects of historical sea level rise and contemporary ocean currents on regional gene flow of rhizopho.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>© 2016 Ngeve et al. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.Mangroves are seafaring taxa through their hydrochorous propagules that have the potential to disperse over long distances. Therefore, investigating their patterns of gene flow provides insights on the processes involved in the spatial genetic structuring of populations. The coastline of Cameroon has a particular geomorphological history and coastal hydrology with complex contemporary patterns of ocean currents, which we hypothesize to have effects on the spatial configuration and composition of present-day mangroves within its spans. A total of 982 trees were sampled from 33 transects (11 sites) in 4 estuaries. Using 11 polymorphic SSR markers, we investigated genetic diversity and structure of Rhizophora racemosa, a widespread species in the region. Genetic diversity was low to moderate and genetic differentiation between nearly all population pairs was significant. Bayesian clustering analysis, PCoA, estimates of contemporary migration rates and identification of barriers to gene flow were used and complemented with estimated dispersal trajectories of hourly released virtual propagules, using high-resolution surface current from a mesoscale and tide-resolving ocean simulation. These indicate that the Cameroon Volcanic Line (CVL) is not a present-day barrier to gene flow. Rather, the Inter-Bioko-Cameroon (IBC) corridor, formed due to sea level rise, allows for connectivity between two mangrove areas that were isolated during glacial times by the CVL. Genetic data and numerical ocean simulations indicated that an oceanic convergence zone near the Cameroon Estuary complex (CEC) presents a strong barrier to gene flow, resulting in genetic discontinuities between the mangrove areas on either side. This convergence did not result in higher genetic diversity at the CEC as we had hypothesized. In conclusion, the genetic structure of Rhizophora racemosa is maintained by the contrasting effects of the contemporary oceanic convergence and historical climate change-induced sea level rise.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Kwok, Ronald</author><author>Hunke, E. C.</author><author>Maslowski, W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Zhang, Jinlun</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Variability of sea ice simulations assessed with RGPS kinematics</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><volume>113</volume><issue>11</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2008</year></dates><isbn>0148-0227</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2008JC004783</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Kwok et al. - 2008 - Variability of sea ice simulations assessed with RGPS kinematics.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Sea ice drift and deformation from coupled ice-ocean models are compared with high-resolution ice motion from the RADARSAT Geophysical Processor System (RGPS). In contrast to buoy drift, the density and extent of the RGPS coverage allows a more extensive assessment and understanding of model simulations at spatial scales from ∼10 km to near basin scales and from days to seasonal timescales. This work illustrates the strengths of the RGPS data set as a basis for examining model ice drift and its gradients. As it is not our intent to assess relative performance, we have selected four models with a range of attributes and grid resolution. Model fields are examined in terms of ice drift, export, deformation, deformation-related ice production, and spatial deformation patterns. Even though the models are capable of reproducing large-scale drift patterns, variability among model behavior is high. When compared to the RGPS kinematics, the characteristics shared by the models are (1) ice drift along coastal Alaska and Siberia is slower, (2) the skill in explaining the time series of regional divergence of the ice cover is poor, and (3) the deformation-related volume production is consistently lower. Attribution of some of these features to specific causes is beyond our current scope because of the complex interplay between model processes, parameters, and forcing. The present work suggests that high-resolution ice drift observations, like those from the RGPS, would be essential for future model developments, improvements, intercomparisons, and especially for evaluation of the small-scale behavior of models with finer grid spacing.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Xu, Yun</author><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author><author>Fenty, Ian G.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Flexas, M. Mar</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Subaqueous melting of Store Glacier, west Greenland from three-dimensional, high-resolution numerical modeling and ocean observations</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>4648-4653</pages><volume>40</volume><issue>17</issue><keywords><keyword>Greenland</keyword><keyword>climate change</keyword><keyword>glaciology</keyword><keyword>hydrology</keyword><keyword>ocean modeling</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/grl.50825</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Xu et al. - 2013 - Subaqueous melting of Store Glacier, west Greenland from three-dimensional, high-resolution numerical modeling and oc.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We present three-dimensional, high-resolution simulations of ice melting at the calving face of Store Glacier, a tidewater glacier in West Greenland, using the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model. We compare the simulated ice melt with an estimate derived from oceanographic data. The simulations show turbulent upwelling and spreading of the freshwater-laden plume along the ice face and the vigorous melting of ice at rates of meters per day. The simulated August 2010 melt rate of 2.0±0.3 m/d is within uncertainties of the melt rate of 3.0±1.0 m/d calculated from oceanographic data. Melting is greatest at depth, above the subglacial channels, causing glacier undercutting. Melt rates increase proportionally to thermal forcing raised to the power of 1.2-1.6 and to subglacial water flux raised to the power of 0.5-0.9. Therefore, in a warmer climate, Store Glacier melting by ocean may increase from both increased ocean temperature and subglacial discharge. Key Points Simulated melt agrees with estimates from a hydrographic survey of the glacier. With more runoff, glaciers will melt faster at constant ocean temperature. ©2013. American Geophysical Union. All Rights Reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Heimbach, Patrick</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Losch, Martin</author><author>Campin, Jean-Michel</author><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>On the formulation of sea-ice models. Part 2: Lessons from multi-year adjoint sea-ice export sensitivities through the Canadian Arctic Archipelago</title><secondary-title>Ocean Modelling</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Ocean Modelling</full-title></periodical><pages>145-158</pages><volume>33</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Adjoint modeling</keyword><keyword>Canadian Arctic Archipelago</keyword><keyword>Coupled ocean and sea-ice model</keyword><keyword>Numerical sea-ice modeling</keyword><keyword>Sea-ice export</keyword><keyword>Sensitivities</keyword><keyword>State estimation</keyword><keyword>Viscous-plastic rheology</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2010</year></dates><isbn>1463-5003</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.ocemod.2010.02.002</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Heimbach et al. - 2010 - On the formulation of sea-ice models. Part 2 Lessons from multi-year adjoint sea-ice export sensitivities throu.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The adjoint of an ocean general circulation model is at the heart of the ocean state estimation system of the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO) project. As part of an ongoing effort to extend ECCO to a coupled ocean/sea-ice estimation system, a dynamic and thermodynamic sea-ice model has been developed for the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm). One key requirement is the ability to generate, by means of automatic differentiation (AD), tangent linear (TLM) and adjoint (ADM) model code for the coupled MITgcm ocean/sea-ice system. This second part of a two-part paper describes aspects of the adjoint model. The adjoint ocean and sea-ice model is used to calculate transient sensitivities of solid (ice and snow) freshwater export through Lancaster Sound in the Canadian Arctic Archipelago (CAA). The adjoint state provides a complementary view of the dynamics. In particular, the transient, multi-year sensitivity patterns reflect dominant pathways and propagation timescales through the CAA as resolved by the model, thus shedding light on causal relationships, in the model, across the Archipelago. The computational cost of inferring such causal relationships from forward model diagnostics alone would be prohibitive. The role of the exact model trajectory around which the adjoint is calculated (and therefore of the exactness of the adjoint) is exposed through calculations using free-slip vs no-slip lateral boundary conditions. Effective ice thickness, sea surface temperature, and precipitation sensitivities, are discussed in detail as examples of the coupled sea-ice/ocean and atmospheric forcing control space. To test the reliability of the adjoint, finite-difference perturbation experiments were performed for each of these elements and the cost perturbations were compared to those &quot; predicted&quot; by the adjoint. Overall, remarkable qualitative and quantitative agreement is found. In particular, the adjoint correctly &quot; predicts&quot; a seasonal sign change in precipitation sensitivities. A physical mechanism for this sign change is presented. The availability of the coupled adjoint opens up the prospect for adjoint-based coupled ocean/sea-ice state estimation. ?? 2010 Elsevier Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author><author>Fenty, Ian G.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Xu, Yun</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Spreading of warm ocean waters around Greenland as a possible cause for glacier acceleration</title><secondary-title>Annals of Glaciology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Annals of Glaciology</full-title></periodical><pages>257-266</pages><volume>53</volume><issue>60</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2012</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.3189/2012AoG60A136</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Rignot et al. - 2012 - Spreading of warm ocean waters around Greenland as a possible cause for glacier acceleration.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We examine the pattern of spreading of warm subtropical-origin waters around Greenland for the years 1992–2009 using a high-resolution (4 km horizontal grid) coupled ocean and sea-ice simulation. The simulation, provided by the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean, Phase II (ECCO2) project, qualitatively reproduces the observed warming of subsurface waters in the subpolar gyre associated with changes of the North Atlantic atmospheric state that occurred in the mid-1990s. The modeled subsurface ocean temperature warmed by 1.58C 8 in southeast and southwest Greenland during 1994–2005 and subsequently cooled by 0.58C; modeled subsurface ocean temperature increased by 2–2.58C in central and then northwest Greenland during 1997–2005 and stabilized thereafter, while it increased after 2005 by &lt;0.58C in north Greenland. Comparisons with in situ measurements off the continental shelf in the Labrador and Irminger Seas indicate that the model initial conditions were 0.48C too warm in the south but the simulated warming is correctly reproduced; while measurements from eastern Baffin Bay reveal that the model initial conditions were 1.08C too cold in the northwest but the simulated ocean warming brought modeled temperature closer to observations, i.e. the simulated warming is 1.08C too large. At several key locations, the modeled oceanic changes off the shelf and below the seasonal mixed layer were rapidly transmitted to the shelf within troughs towards (model-unresolved) fjords. Unless blocked in the fjords by shallow sills, these warm subsurface waters had potential to propagate down the fjords and melt the glacier fronts. Based on model sensitivity simulations from an independent study (Xu and others, 2012), we show that the oceanic changes have very likely increased the subaqueous melt rates of the glacier fronts, and in turn impacted the rates of glacier flow.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Lee, Tong</author><author>Cheng, Benny</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The origin, pathway, and destination of Niño-3 water estimated by a simulated passive tracer and its adjoint</title><secondary-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>582-604</pages><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/2515.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fukumori et al. - 2004 - The origin, pathway, and destination of Niño-3 water estimated by a simulated passive tracer and its adjoint.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/abs/10.1175/2515.1</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The nature of subtropical - tropical water mass exchange in the Pacific Ocean is investigated, focusing on the origin, pathway, and destination of water occupying the surface layer of the eastern equatorial Pacific Ocean (Nino-3 region; 5degreesS - 5degreesN, 150degrees - 90degreesW). Simulated passive tracers and their adjoint are employed to explicitly follow the circulation of specific water masses accounting for advective and diffusive effects and their time variabilities. The evolution of the forward passive tracer and adjoint passive tracer can be identified as describing where the tracer-tagged water mass goes and from where it comes, respectively. Over 10 years on average, water mass of the Nino-3 region can be traced back to eastern subtropical thermocline waters of the Northern (27%) and Southern Hemispheres (39%). The Nino-3 water subsequently returns to these subtropical latitudes in the upper ocean. In contrast to the hypothesized &quot;subtropical cell,'' however, this circulation is an open circuit with water returning to the western regions of the two hemispheres ( subtropical gyres) and to the Indian Ocean, instead of returning to its origins. The representative transit time scale from the subtropics to the Tropics is 10 15 yr. Temporal variability causes the tropical circulation inferred from a time-mean state to differ significantly from the average circulation. In particular, stirring due to nonseasonal, intra-annual variability significantly enhances the transport magnitude of the so-called interior pathways relative to that of the circuitous low-latitude western boundary pathways. Such short-circuit in the subtropical - tropical exchange may help better to explain tracer distributions, such as the observed midbasin tritium maximum in the equatorial Pacific Ocean. Significant differences in circulation pathways are also identified that are associated with El Nino and La Nina events. The strength of the subtropical - tropical water mass exchange is estimated to have weakened during the 1990s.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Schodlok, Michael P.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author><author>Studinger, Michael</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sensitivity of the ice-shelf/ocean system to the sub-ice-shelf cavity shape measured by nasa icebridge in pine island glacier, west antarctica</title><secondary-title>Annals of Glaciology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Annals of Glaciology</full-title></periodical><pages>156-162</pages><volume>53</volume><issue>60</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2012</year></dates><isbn>0260-3055</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.3189/2012AoG60A073</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Schodlok et al. - 2012 - Sensitivity of the ice-shelfocean system to the sub-ice-shelf cavity shape measured by nasa icebridge in pine i.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Two high-resolution (1 km grid) numerical model simulations of the Amundsen Sea, West Antarctica, are used to study the role of the ocean in the mass loss and grounding line retreat of Pine Island Glacier. The first simulation uses BEDMAP bathymetry under the Pine Island ice shelf, and the second simulation uses NASA IceBridge-derived bathymetry. The IceBridge data reveal the existence of a trough from the ice-shelf edge to the grounding line, enabling warm Circumpolar Deep Water to penetrate to the grounding line, leading to higher melt rates than previously estimated. The mean melt rate for the simulation with NASA IceBridge data is 28ma–1, much higher than previous model estimates but closer to estimates from remote sensing. Although the mean melt rate is 25% higher than in the simulation with BEDMAP bathymetry, the temporal evolution remains unchanged between the two simulations. This indicates that temporal variability of melting is mostly driven by processes outside the cavity. Spatial melt rate patterns of BEDMAP and IceBridge simulations differ significantly, with the latter in closer agreement with satellite-derived melt rate estimates of 50ma–1 near the grounding line. Our simulations confirm that knowledge of the cavity shape and its time evolution are essential to accurately capture basal mass loss of Antarctic ice shelves.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Farmer, David M.</author><author>Czipott, Peter V.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A note on infragravity waves in the Arctic Ocean water just beneath the ice of order sensitivity</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research</full-title></periodical><pages>7089-7093</pages><volume>100</volume><issue>C4</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1995</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Farmer, Czipott - 1995 - A note on infragravity waves in the Arctic Ocean water just beneath the ice of order sensitivity.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Long-period (20-50 s) surface-gravity waves were recorded in the eastern Arctic using tiltmeters deployed on the ice and an acoustical current meter deployed a few meters below the ice during the spring of 1989. The waves caused ice tilt of a few microradians and horizontal velocity of the water just beneath the ice of order 10-4 m s-1. The sensitivity of the velocity measurements is the result of a path-averaging technique based on reciprocal transmission along 200-m horizontal paths. The measurements indicate that infragravity waves and low-frequency swell penetrate the Arctic Ocean through the Fram Strait and that they are freely propagating and not tied to groups of short waves. It is suggested that these waves could provide a method to measure ice thickness distribution in the Arctic Ocean. -Authors</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Hill, Christopher N.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Ciotti, Robert B.</author><author>Henze, Christopher E.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Investigating solution convergence in a global ocean model using a 2048-processor cluster of distributed shared memory machines</title><secondary-title>Scientific Programming</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Scientific Programming</full-title></periodical><pages>107-115</pages><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>computational fluid dynamics</keyword><keyword>ocean modeling</keyword><keyword>parallel computing</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2007</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1155/2007/458463</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Hill et al. - 2007 - Investigating solution convergence in a global ocean model using a 2048-processor cluster of distributed shared mem.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Up to 1920 processors of a cluster of distributed shared memory machines at the NASA Ames Research Center are being used to simulate ocean circulation globally at horizontal resolutions of 1/4, 1/8, and 1/16-degree with the Massachusetts Institute of Technology General Circulation Model, a finite volume code that can scale to large numbers of processors. The study aims to understand physical processes responsible for skill improvements as resolution is increased and to gain insight into what resolution is sufficient for particular purposes. This paper focuses on the computational aspects of reaching the technical objective of efficiently performing these global eddy-resolving ocean simulations. At 1/16-degree resolution the model grid contains 1.2 billion cells. At this resolution it is possible to simulate approximately one month of ocean dynamics in about 17 hours of wallclock time with a model timestep of two minutes on a cluster of four 512-way NUMA Altix systems. The Altix systems' large main memory and I/O subsystems allow computation and disk storage of rich sets of diagnostics during each integration, supporting the scientific objective to develop a better understanding of global ocean circulation model solution convergence as model resolution is increased.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gross, Richard S.</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Atmospheric and oceanic excitation of decadal-scale Earth orientation variations</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research B: Solid Earth</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research B: Solid Earth</full-title></periodical><volume>110</volume><issue>9</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2005</year></dates><isbn>0148-0227</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2004JB003565</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gross, Fukumori, Menemenlis - 2005 - Atmospheric and oceanic excitation of decadal-scale Earth orientation variations.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The contribution of atmospheric wind and surface pressure and oceanic current and bottom pressure variations during 1949–2002 to exciting changes in the Earth's orientation on decadal timescales is investigated using an atmospheric angular momentum series computed from the National Centers for Environmental Prediction/National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCEP/NCAR) reanalysis project and an oceanic angular momentum series computed from a near-global ocean model that was forced by surface fluxes from the NCEP/NCAR reanalysis project. Not surprisingly, since decadal-scale variations in the length of day are caused mainly by interactions between the mantle and core, the effect of the atmosphere and oceans is found to be only about 14% of that observed. More surprisingly, it is found that the effect of atmospheric and oceanic processes on decadal-scale changes in polar motion is also only about 20% (x component) and 38% (y component) of that observed. Therefore redistribution of mass within the atmosphere and oceans does not appear to be the main cause of the Markowitz wobble. It is also found that on timescales between 10 days and 4 years the atmospheric and oceanic angular momentum series used here have very little skill in explaining Earth orientation variations before the mid to late 1970s. This is attributed to errors in both the Earth orientation observations prior to 1976 when measurements from the accurate space-geodetic techniques became available and to errors in the modeled atmospheric fields prior to 1979 when the satellite era of global weather observing systems began.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Lee, Tong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Atlantic to Mediterranean Sea Level Difference Driven by Winds near Gibraltar Strait</title><secondary-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Physical Oceanography</full-title></periodical><pages>359-376</pages><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2007</year></dates><isbn>0022-3670</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1175/JPO3015.1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Fukumori, Lee - 2007 - Atlantic to Mediterranean Sea Level Difference Driven by Winds near Gibraltar Strait.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Observations and numerical simulations show that winds near Gibraltar Strait cause an Atlantic Ocean to Mediterranean Sea sea level difference of 20 cm peak to peak with a 3-cm standard deviation for periods of days to years. Theoretical arguments and numerical experiments establish that this wind-driven sea level difference is caused in part by storm surges due to alongshore winds near the North African coastline on the Atlantic side of Gibraltar. The fraction of the Moroccan coastal current offshore of the 284-m isobath is deflected across Gibraltar Strait, west of Camarinal Sill, resulting in a geostrophic surface pressure gradient that contributes to a sea level difference at the stationary limit. The sea level difference is also caused in part by the along-strait wind setup, with a contribution proportional to the along- strait wind stress and to the length of Gibraltar Strait and adjoining regions and inversely proportional to its depth. In the 20 - 360-day band, average transfer coefficients between the Atlantic - Alboran sea level difference and surface wind stress at 36 degrees N, 6.5 degrees W, estimated from barometrically corrected Ocean Topography Experiment ( TOPEX)/Poseidon data and NCEP - NCAR reanalysis data, are 0.10 +/- 0.04 m Pa-1 with 1 +/- 5-day lag and 0.19 +/- 0.08 m Pa-1 with 5 +/- 4-day lag for the zonal and meridional wind stresses, respectively. This transfer function is consistent with equivalent estimates derived from a 1992 - 2003 high-resolution barotropic simulation forced by the NCEP - NCAR wind stress. The barotropic simulation explains 29% of the observed Atlantic - Alboran sea level difference in the 20 - 360-day band. In turn, the Alboran and Mediterranean mean sea level time series are highly correlated, rho = 0.7 in the observations and rho = 0.8 in the barotropic simulation, hence providing a pathway for winds near Gibraltar Strait to affect the mean sea level of the entire Mediterranean.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Wang, Xiaochun</author><author>Zhao, L.</author><author>Li, Zhijin</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Regional ocean forecasting systems and their applications: Design considerations of such a system for the South China Sea</title><secondary-title>Aquatic Ecosystem Health and Management</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Aquatic Ecosystem Health and Management</full-title></periodical><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords><keyword>Regional Oc</keyword><keyword>[data assimilation</keyword><keyword>ensemble</keyword><keyword>nesting</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/14634988.2015.1112123</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Wang et al. - 2015 - Regional ocean forecasting systems and their applications Design considerations of such a system for the South Chin.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>© 2015 AEHMS.Essential components and technical details of regional ocean forecasting systems configured from the Regional Ocean Modeling System are discussed with the goal of bridging the gap between user and ocean modeling communities. Recent development of these systems and applications are also surveyed. Design considerations of such a system for the South China Sea are discussed, based on regional dynamic characteristics and potential applications.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Whitefield, Jonathan</author><author>Winsor, Peter</author><author>McClelland, James W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A new river discharge and river temperature climatology data set for the pan-Arctic region</title><secondary-title>Ocean Modelling</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Ocean Modelling</full-title></periodical><pages>1-15</pages><volume>88</volume><keywords><keyword>Arctic Ocean</keyword><keyword>Climatology</keyword><keyword>Heat content</keyword><keyword>Modelling</keyword><keyword>River discharge</keyword><keyword>Sea ice</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.ocemod.2014.12.012</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Whitefield et al. - 2015 - A new river discharge and river temperature climatology data set for the pan-Arctic region.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Most regional ocean models that use discharge as part of the forcing use relatively coarse river discharge data sets (1??, or ~110km) compared to the model resolution (typically 1/4?? or less), and do not account for seasonal changes in river water temperature. We introduce a new climatological data set of river discharge and river water temperature with 1/6?? grid spacing over the Arctic region (Arctic River Discharge and Temperature; ARDAT), incorporating observations from 30 Arctic rivers. The annual mean discharge for all rivers in ARDAT is 2817??330km3yr-1. River water temperatures range between 0??C in winter to 14.0-17.6??C in July, leading to a long-term mean monthly heat flux from all rivers of 3.2??0.6TW, of which 31% is supplied by Alaskan rivers and 69% is supplied by Eurasian rivers. This riverine heat flux is equivalent to 44% of the estimated ocean heat flux associated with the Bering Strait throughflow, but during the spring freshet can be ~10 times as large, suggesting that heat flux associated with Arctic rivers is an important component of the Arctic heat budget on seasonal time scales.We apply the ARDAT data set to a high-resolution regional ocean-ice model, and compare results to a model integration using a 1?? resolution discharge data set. Integrated freshwater content on the Arctic shelves (&lt;200m) increases by ~3600km3 in the ARDAT forced model run compared to the coarser forcing, suggesting that river discharge is contained on the Arctic shelves when forced with the ARDAT data set. Modelled summer heat fluxes over the shelves increase by 8TW when river water temperature is included, which subsequently reduces basin-wide September sea ice extent by ~10%. Regional differences are larger, where e.g., sea ice extent on the Beaufort shelf is reduced by ~36%. Using a non-linear free surface parameterization along with the ARDAT data set, we find an increase in the sea surface height gradient around river mouths. Geostrophic velocities increase to form quasi-continuous, fast-moving near-shore boundary currents not reproduced using the 1?? resolution data set. Omitting river water temperature, or using a lower resolution data set, can therefore lead to incorrect model estimates of coastal transport, sea ice formation/melt rates, and other regional and basin scale processes. Using a high-resolution discharge data set, and accounting for the considerable heat carried by the Arctic rivers is recommended for future modelling efforts.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Generic">31</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Spreen, Gunnar</author><author>Kwok, Ronald</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Trends in Arctic sea ice drift and role of wind forcing: 1992-2009</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><volume>38</volume><issue>19</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2011</year></dates><isbn>0094-8276</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2011GL048970</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Spreen, Kwok, Menemenlis - 2011 - Trends in Arctic sea ice drift and role of wind forcing 1992-2009.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We examine the spatial trends in Arctic sea ice drift speed from satellite\ndata and the role of wind forcing for the winter months of October\nthrough May. Between 1992 and 2009, the spatially averaged trend\nin drift speed within the Arctic Basin is 10.6% � 0.9%/decade, and\nranges between &amp;#8722;4% and 16%/decade depending on the location.\nThe mean trend is dominated by the second half of the period. In\nfact, for the five years after a clear break point in March 2004,\nthe average trend increased to 46% � 5%/decade. Over the 1992&amp;#8211;2009\nperiod, averaged trends of wind speed from four atmospheric reanalyses\nare only 1% to 2%/decade. Regionally, positive trends in wind speed\n(of up to 9%/decade) are seen over a large fraction of the Central\nArctic, where the trends in drift speeds are highest. Spatial correlations\nbetween the basin-wide trends in wind and drift speeds are moderate\n(between 0.40 and 0.52). Our results suggest that changes in wind\nspeed explain a fraction of the observed increase in drift speeds\nin the Central Arctic but not over the entire basin. In other regions\nthinning of the ice cover is a more likely cause of the increase\nin ice drift speed.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Nguyen, An T.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Kwok, Ronald</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Arctic ice-ocean simulation with optimized model parameters: Approach and assessment</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><volume>116</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2011</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2010JC006573</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Nguyen, Menemenlis, Kwok - 2011 - Arctic ice-ocean simulation with optimized model parameters Approach and assessment.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We present an optimized 1992–2008 coupled ice-ocean simulation of the Arctic Ocean. A Green's function approach adjusts a set of parameters for best model-data agreement. Overall, model-data differences are reduced by 45%. The optimized simulation reproduces the negative trends in ice extent in the satellite records. Volume and thickness distributions are comparable to those from the Ice, Cloud, and land Elevation Satellite (2003–2008). The upper cold halocline is consistent with observations in the western Arctic. The freshwater budget of the Arctic Ocean and volume/heat transports of Pacific and Atlantic waters across major passages are comparable with observation-based estimates. We note that the optimized parameters depend on the selected atmospheric forcing. The use of the 25 year Japanese reanalysis results in sea ice albedos that are consistent with field observations. Simulated Pacific Water enters the Bering Strait and flows off the Chukchi Shelf along four distinct channels. This water takes ∼5–10 years to exit the Arctic Ocean at the Canadian Arctic Archipelago, Nares, or Fram straits. Atlantic Water entering the Fram Strait flows eastward, merges with the St Ana Trough inflow, and splits into two branches at the southwest corner of the Makarov Basin. One branch flows along Lomonosov Ridge back to Fram Strait. The other enters the western Arctic, circulates cyclonically below the halocline, and exits mainly through the Nares and Fram straits. This work utilizes the record of available observations to obtain an Arctic Ocean simulation that is in agreement with observations both within and beyond the optimization period and that can be used for tracer and process studies.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Schodlok, Michael P.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Rignot, Eric J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Ice shelf basal melt rates around Antarctica from simulations and observations</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>1085-1109</pages><volume>121</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Antarctica</keyword><keyword>Southern Ocean</keyword><keyword>ice shelf basal melt</keyword><keyword>ice shelf ocean interaction</keyword><keyword>numerical modeling</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2015JC011117</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Schodlok, Menemenlis, Rignot - 2016 - Ice shelf basal melt rates around Antarctica from simulations and observations.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We introduce an explicit representation of Antarctic ice shelf cavities in the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean, Phase II (ECCO2) ocean retrospective analysis; and compare resulting basal melt rates and patterns to independent estimates from satellite observations. Two simulations are carried out: the first is based on the original ECCO2 vertical discretization; the second has higher vertical resolution particularly at the depth range of ice shelf cavities. The original ECCO2 vertical discretization produces higher than observed melt rates and leads to a misrepresentation of Southern Ocean water mass properties and transports. In general, thicker levels at the base of the ice shelves lead to increased melting because of their larger heat capacity. This strengthens horizontal gradients and circulation within and outside the cavities and, in turn, warm water transports from the shelf break to the ice shelves. The simulation with more vertical levels produces basal melt rates (1735 ± 164 Gt/a) and patterns that are in better agreement with observations. Thinner levels in the sub-ice-shelf cavities improve the representation of a fresh/cold layer at the ice shelf base and of warm/salty water near the bottom, leading to a sharper pycnocline and reduced vertical mixing underneath the ice shelf. Improved water column properties lead to more accurate melt rates and patterns, especially for melt/freeze patterns under large cold-water ice shelves. At the 18 km grid spacing of the ECCO2 model configuration, the smaller, warm-water ice shelves cannot be properly represented, with higher than observed melt rates in both simulations.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fieguth, Paul W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mapping and pseudoinverse algorithms for ocean data assimilation</title><secondary-title>IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing</full-title></periodical><pages>43-51</pages><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords><keyword>Climatological models</keyword><keyword>Data assimilation</keyword><keyword>Interscale transforms</keyword><keyword>Pseudoinverse methods</keyword><keyword>Remote sensing</keyword><keyword>Sparse pseudoinverses</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><isbn>0196-2892</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/TGRS.2002.808058</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fieguth, Menemenlis, Fukumori - 2003 - Mapping and pseudoinverse algorithms for ocean data assimilation.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Among existing ocean data assimilation methodologies, reduced-state Kalman filters are a widely studied compromise between resolution, optimality, error specification, and computational feasibility. In such reduced-state filters, the measurement update takes place on a coarser grid than that of the general circulation model (GCM); therefore, these filters require mapping operators from the GCM grid to the reduced state and vice versa. The general requirements are that the state-reduction and interpolation operators be pseudoinverses of each other, that the coarse state define a closed dynamical system, that the mapping operations be insensitive to noise, and that they be appropriate for regions with irregular coastlines and bathymetry. In this paper, we describe three efficient algorithms for computing the pseudoinverse: a fast Fourier transform algorithm that serves for illustration purposes, an exact implicit method that is recommended for most applications, and an efficient iterative algorithm that can be used for the largest problems. The mapping performance of 11 interpolation kernels is evaluated. Surprisingly, common kernels such as bilinear, exponential, Gaussian, and sinc perform only moderately well. We recommend instead three kernels, smooth, thin-plate, and optimal interpolation, which have superior properties. This study removes the computational bottleneck of mapping and pseudoinverse algorithms and makes possible the application of reduced-state filters to global problems at state-of-the-art resolutions.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gross, Richard S.</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Atmospheric and oceanic excitation of the Earth's wobbles during 1980–2000</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research B: Solid Earth</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research B: Solid Earth</full-title></periodical><volume>108</volume><issue>B8</issue><keywords><keyword>1223 Geodesy and Gravity: Ocean/Earth/atmosphere i</keyword><keyword>1239 Geodesy and Gravity: Rotational variations</keyword><keyword>3319 Meteorology and Atmospheric Dynamics: General</keyword><keyword>4532 Oceanography: Physical: General circulation</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><isbn>0148-0227</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2002JB002143</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gross, Fukumori, Menemenlis - 2003 - Atmospheric and oceanic excitation of the Earth's wobbles during 1980–2000.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2002JB002143</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Because of the action of various geophysical excitation mechanisms, the Earth does not rotate about its figure axis, so it wobbles as it rotates. Here, the effectiveness of atmospheric and oceanic processes in exciting the Earth's wobbles during 1980–2000 is evaluated using estimates of atmospheric angular momentum from the National Centers for Environmental Prediction/National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCEP/NCAR) reanalysis project and estimates of oceanic angular momentum from the Estimating the Circulation and Climate of the Ocean (ECCO) consortium's simulation of the general circulation of the oceans. On intraseasonal timescales, atmospheric surface pressure changes are found to be the single most effective process exciting the Earth's wobbles, explaining about twice as much of the observed variance as do either atmospheric wind or ocean bottom pressure changes and nearly 4 times as much of the observed variance as do oceanic currents. However, on interannual timescales, ocean bottom pressure changes are found to be the single most effective process exciting the Earth's wobbles, explaining more than 5 times as much of the observed variance as do atmospheric wind and pressure changes combined, and more than twice as much of the observed variance as do oceanic currents. Within the Chandler band it is found that during 1980&amp;#8211;2000 atmospheric and oceanic processes have enough power to excite the Chandler wobble and are significantly coherent with it. The single most important mechanism exciting the Chandler wobble is found to be ocean bottom pressure variations. Atmospheric and oceanic processes do not appear to have enough power to excite the Earth's wobbles to their observed levels on pentadal and longer timescales, although series longer than the 21-yearlong series used here need to be studied in order to obtain greater statistical significance of this result.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rocha, Cesar B.</author><author>Gille, Sarah T.</author><author>Chereskin, Teresa K.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Seasonality of submesoscale dynamics in the Kuroshio Extension</title><secondary-title>Geophysical Research Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geophysical Research Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>11304-11311</pages><volume>43</volume><issue>21</issue><keywords><keyword>COMPIRA</keyword><keyword>Kuroshio Extension</keyword><keyword>SWOT</keyword><keyword>inertia-gravity waves</keyword><keyword>submesoscale dynamics</keyword><keyword>submesoscale turbulence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2016GL071349</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Rocha et al. - 2016 - Seasonality of submesoscale dynamics in the Kuroshio Extension.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Recent studies show that the vigorous seasonal cycle of the mixed layer modulates upper ocean submesoscale turbulence. Here we provide model-based evidence that the seasonally changing upper ocean stratification in the Kuroshio Extension also modulates submesoscale (here 10–100 km) inertia-gravity waves. Summertime restratification weakens submesoscale turbulence but enhances inertia-gravity waves near the surface. Thus, submesoscale turbulence and inertia-gravity waves undergo vigorous out-of-phase seasonal cycles. These results imply a strong seasonal modulation of the accuracy of geostrophic velocity diagnosed from submesoscale sea surface height delivered by the SurfaceWater and Ocean Topography satellite mission.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dushaw, Brian D.</author><author>Worcester, Peter F.</author><author>Dzieciuch, Matthew A.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>On the time-mean state of ocean models and the properties of long range acoustic propagation</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><pages>4346-4362</pages><volume>118</volume><issue>9</issue><keywords><keyword>acoustic thermometry</keyword><keyword>model testing</keyword><keyword>ocean models</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/jgrc.20325</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dushaw et al. - 2013 - On the time-mean state of ocean models and the properties of long range acoustic propagation.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Receptions on three vertical hydrophone arrays from basin-scale acoustic transmissions in the North Pacific during 1996 and 1998 are used to test the time-mean sound-speed properties of the World Ocean Atlas 2005 (WOA05), of an eddying unconstrained simulation of the Parallel Ocean Program (POP), and of three data-constrained solutions provided by the estimating the circulation and climate of the ocean (ECCO) project: a solution based on an approximate Kalman filter from the Jet Propulsion Laboratory (ECCO-JPL), a solution based on the adjoint method from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (ECCO-MIT), and an eddying solution based on a Green's function approach from ECCO, Phase II (ECCO2). Predictions for arrival patterns using annual average WOA05 fields match observations to within small travel time offsets (0.3-1.0 s). Predictions for arrival patterns from the models differ substantially from the measured arrival patterns, from the WOA05 climatology, and from each other, both in terms of travel time and in the structure of the arrival patterns. The acoustic arrival patterns are sensitive to the vertical gradients of sound speed that govern acoustic propagation. Basin-scale acoustic transmissions, therefore, provide stringent tests of the vertical temperature structure of ocean state estimates. This structure ultimately influences the mixing between the surface waters and the ocean interior. The relatively good agreement of the acoustic data with the more recent ECCO solutions indicates that numerical ocean models have reached a level of accuracy where the acoustic data can provide useful additional constraints for ocean state estimation. © 2013. American Geophysical Union. All Rights Reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Miller, Madeline D.</author><author>Adkins, Jess F.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Schodlok, Michael P.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The role of ocean cooling in setting glacial southern source bottom water salinity</title><secondary-title>Paleoceanography</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Paleoceanography</full-title></periodical><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2012</year></dates><isbn>1944-9186</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2012PA002297</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Miller et al. - 2012 - The role of ocean cooling in setting glacial southern source bottom water salinity.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>At the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM), the salinity contrast between northern source deep water and southern source bottom water was reversed with respect to the contrast today. Additionally, Glacial Southern Source Bottom Water (GSSBW) was saltier than Antarctic Bottom Water (AABW), over and above the difference implied by the mean sea level change. This study examines to what extent cold temperatures, through their effect on ice formation and melting, could have caused these differences. Computational sensitivity experiments using a coupled ice shelf cavity–sea ice–ocean model are performed in a Weddell Sea domain, as a representative case study for bottom water formation originating from Antarctic continental shelves. Ocean temperatures at the domain open boundaries are systematically lowered to determine the sensitivity of Weddell Sea water mass properties to a range of cool ocean temperatures. The steady state salinities differ between experiments due to temperature-induced responses of ice shelf and sea ice melting and freezing, evaporation and open boundary fluxes. The results of the experiments indicate that reduced ocean temperature can explain up to 30% of the salinity difference between GSSBW and AABW, primarily due to decreased ice shelf melting. The smallest and most exposed ice shelves, which abut narrow continental shelves, have the greatest sensitivity to the ocean temperature changes, suggesting that at the LGM there could have been a shift in geographical site dominance in bottom water formation. More sea ice is formed and exported in the cold ocean experiments, but the effect of this on salinity is negated by an equal magnitude reduction in evaporation.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Nguyen, An T.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Kwok, Ronald</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Improved modeling of the arctic halocline with a subgrid-scale brine rejection parameterization</title><secondary-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</full-title></periodical><volume>114</volume><issue>11</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><isbn>0148-0227</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2008JC005121</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Nguyen, Menemenlis, Kwok - 2009 - Improved modeling of the arctic halocline with a subgrid-scale brine rejection parameterization.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The halocline in the Arctic Ocean plays an important role in regulating\nheat exchange at the bottom of the mixed layer and it has a direct\neffect on the ocean sea ice energy balance and sea ice mass balance.\nModeling the halocline, however, remains a challenge in current state-of-the-art\ncoupled ocean sea ice models including those that participated in\nthe Arctic Ocean Model Intercomparison Project. In this study, we\nsuccessfully reproduce a cold halocline in the Canada Basin by implementing\na subgrid-scale brine rejection parameterization in an ocean general\ncirculation model. The brine rejection scheme improves the solution\nby redistributing surface salts rejected during sea ice formation\nto their neutral buoyancy depths. The depths are based on salt plume\nphysics and published laboratory and numerical experiments. Compared\nwith hydrographic data from 1993 to 2004, distribution of most of\nthe rejected salt to the bottom of the mixed layer seems to yield\nthe lowest model-data misfits. We also show that the model's mixed\nlayer depth is sensitive to the background diffusivity &amp;#957; used\nin the k-profile parameterization vertical mixing scheme. A background\ndiffusivity of 10&amp;#8722;6 m2/s in combination with brine rejection\nscheme described herein yield the best simulation of the Arctic halocline.</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Farmer, David M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Acoustical measurement of current and vorticity beneath ice</title><secondary-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology</full-title></periodical><pages>827-849</pages><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1992</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Menemenlis, Farmer - 1992 - Acoustical measurement of current and vorticity beneath ice.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>An acoustical instrument has been developed to measure path-averaged horizontal current and vorticity in the subice boundary layer of the eastern Arctic during the spring of 1989. A triangular acoustic array of side 200 m was used to obtain reciprocal transmission measurements at 132 kHz, at 8, 10, and 20 m beneath an ice floe. Pseudorandom coding and real-time signal processing provided precise acoustic travel time and amplitude for each reciprocal path. Performance of the method is discussed. -from Authors</abstract></record><record><database name="My Collection.enl" path="My Collection.enl">My Collection.enl</database><ref-type name="Conference Proceedings">3</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Fieguth, Paul W.</author><author>Menemenlis, Dimitris</author><author>Fukumori, Ichiro</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mapping and pseudo-inverse algorithms for data assimilation</title><secondary-title>IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium</full-title></periodical><pages>3221-3223</pages><volume>6</volume><keywords><keyword>Data assimilation</keyword><keyword>FFT</keyword><keyword>Filters</keyword><keyword>GCM grid</keyword><keyword>Interpolation</keyword><keyword>Iterative algorithms</keyword><keyword>Iterative methods</keyword><keyword>Kalman filters</keyword><keyword>Kernel</keyword><keyword>Oceanographic techniques</keyword><keyword>Oceans</keyword><keyword>Performance evaluation</keyword><keyword>Sea measurements</keyword><keyword>bathymetry</keyword><keyword>closed dynamical system</keyword><keyword>coarse state</keyword><keyword>computational bottleneck</keyword><keyword>data assimilation</keyword><keyword>general circulation model</keyword><keyword>geophysical signal processing</keyword><keyword>implicit methods</keyword><keyword>interpolation</keyword><keyword>interpolation operators</keyword><keyword>irregular coastlines</keyword><keyword>iterative approach</keyword><keyword>mapping algorithms</keyword><keyword>ocean data assimilation methodologies</keyword><keyword>oceanographic techniques</keyword><keyword>pseudo-inverse algorithms</keyword><keyword>reduced order systems</keyword><keyword>reduced-state Kalman filters</keyword><keyword>reduced-state filters</keyword><keyword>state-reduction</keyword><keyword>subsampling methods</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2002</year></dates><isbn>0-7803-7536-X</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1109/IGARSS.2002.1027136</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Fieguth, Menemenlis, Fukumori - 2002 - Mapping and pseudo-inverse algorithms for data assimilation.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/lpdocs/epic03/wrapper.htm?arnumber=1027136</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Among existing ocean data assimilation methodologies, reduced-state Kalman filters are a widely-studied compromise between resolution, optimality, error specification, and computational feasibility. In such reduced-state filters, the measurement update takes place on a coarser grid than that of the general circulation model (GCM); therefore, these filters require mapping operators from the GCM grid to the reduced state and vice-versa. The general requirements are that the state-reduction and interpolation operators be pseudo-inverses of each other, that the coarse state defines a closed dynamical system, that the mapping operations be insensitive to noise, and that they be appropriate for regions with irregular coastlines and bathymetry. In this paper we investigate a variety of approaches, including computing the pseudoinverse by brute force, using the FFT, subsampling methods, implicit methods, and finally develop a novel iterative approach. We also evaluate the mapping performance of eleven interpolation kernels; surprisingly, common kernels such as bilinear, exponential, Gaussian, and sinc, performed only moderately well. This comprehensive study greatly reduces the computational bottleneck and guesswork of pseudo-inverse algorithms, making possible the application of reduced-state filters to global problems at state-of-the-art resolution.</abstract></record></records></xml>
